<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the life and death of the Blessed Virgin according to Romish writers with the grounds of the worship paid to her, and a preface in answer to the Apology for the Contemplations, &amp;c. / by a lay hand.</title>
            <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39732</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12680020</idno>
  <idno type="VID">65623</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248570064</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20666</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12680020</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 353:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the life and death of the Blessed Virgin according to Romish writers with the grounds of the worship paid to her, and a preface in answer to the Apology for the Contemplations, &amp;c. / by a lay hand.</title>
                  <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], xliii, 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Clark, for Thomas Newborough ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The following piece is none of my own, but a learned and renowned Frenchman's, which I have drest up in English, with some little alteration of the style, and addition of some little matters"--Pref.</note>
                  <note>The preface "To J.C.D.D." [i.e. John Cross] is a reply to that author's "Apology for the Contemplations on the life and glory of the holy mother of Jesus."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to William Fleetwood. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, June 7, 1687, Hen. Maurice"--P. at beginning.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cross, John, 1630-1689. --  Apology for the Contemplations on the life and glory of the holy mother of Jesus.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:65623:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HEN. MAƲRICE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 7. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65623:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Life and Death</hi> OF THE Blessed Virgin, According to <hi>Romish</hi> Writers.</p>
            <p>WITH THE Grounds of the WORSHIP paid to Her. AND <hi>A</hi> PREFACE <hi>in Answer to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for the Contemplations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Lay Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Clark,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Newborough</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65623:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:65623:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> J. C. <hi>D. D.</hi> Author of the Contemplations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Apology.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Present You here with <hi>A Short Account of the Life and Death of the ever blessed Virgin,</hi> collected from Authors truly Catholick, and zealous Devoto's; such, as in all likelihood, had long ago performed your Eight Acts of Special Devotion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her. If I could have got my self to have made some Resolutions, some Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Praises, Versicles, Responses, Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and Anthems, to have turned Psalms of <hi>David</hi> from our Lord to our Lady, and composed some hobling Hymns, with a Covenant at the last, I am persuaded this Book might have passed for a Second Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with some Alterations, of <hi>Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> on the Life and Glory of Holy <hi>Mary.</hi> There is so near an Affinity between the
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:65623:3"/> Doctrines of them both, the Authors are so very like, the Matter and Substance of them is so very much the same, that I think I have sufficient claim to your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage; and may reasonably shelter my self under the Protection of your Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, which will serve for the one, as well as the other: and I cannot but congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the good fortune of my Book, that it was born with its Defence ready made. To give you my judgment freely on the matter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> verily believe your two Books are a more fair and full Exposition of the Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> in this Point, than what our <hi>Representer,</hi> Mr. <hi>de Meaux,</hi> or his <hi>Vindicator</hi> have given us; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Universal Practice of your Church is concordant with, and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondent to Your Principles, but by no means to Theirs. For what an intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable injury must there be done to plain natural sence, what extreme violence must there be used, to pull and reduce to a plain <hi>Ord pro▪ nobis,</hi> such noble and exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed flights, such vast, exuberant, <hi>seraphical</hi> and <hi>supereminential strains,</hi> as are every where to be met withal in the Authors of the <hi>Virginal Sodality?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:65623:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And thou, O most glorious and powerful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Contempl. pag. 86.</note>
               <hi>of God, pity me, and protect me; for thou art highly acceptable to God, canst obtain Mercies, and wilt procure a Mission of Angels to relieve me, that my Soul may rejoyce in thy fulness and bounty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore (for the same reason) now for</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
               <hi>ever, I chuse thee, O glorious Mother of</hi> Jesus, <hi>to be my Patroness, Advocate, and Adoptive Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, admit me, O powerful Queen of Angels, amongst thy Clients: Suppress my Enemies; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage my Cause in the Court of our Requests,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>—<hi>And thou, O Mother of Mercy, dost still</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 99.</note>
               <hi>sollicit my Cause at the Throne of thy Son's boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, art watchful over my motions and dost compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionate my failings. Help, quicken, triumph over my weak desires. Take me into the Arms of thy Pity. Suffer not the Image of</hi> Jesus <hi>to be razed forth my Spirit, since I have been redeemed, washed and watred with the Blood of</hi> Jesus, <hi>taken forth of the Centre of thy Amorous Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋnto thy Custody I commit and recommend my</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 101.</note>
               <hi>self, with all the powers, passions, and motions▪ of my body and mind; and all living and dead; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intreating thee, through all thy Mercies and Merits, Priviledges and Power, and by whatever is dearest unto thee, that we may be admitted to
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:65623:4"/> be thy Children, Servants, and Devotees; that we may be protected, directed and assisted, and comforted by thee: and that by thee, we may be presented to God the Father who created us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You will scorn, I think, to have such Sentences as these (and greater yet than these, if I had leisure to select them) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a poor <hi>Ora pro nobis.</hi> But your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, that those dry, insipid <hi>Ora pro nobis</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Gentlemen are but very few in number, and dare hardly shew themselves but in the Days and Kingdoms of Conversion. But for a couple of Unreasonable Men, commend me to the Modern Opposers of your Contemplations, the one a <hi>Friendly</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apology, Pag. 13.</note>
               <hi>Trimmer, (Speculum B. Virg.</hi>) the other an open <hi>Vigilantian (Answer to a Catholick Misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented</hi>). With the first, joyn all those Misbelievers, who will not away with<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> sound and wholsom Meats, unless they be also toothsom, who so trim in this great Point of Christian Piety towards the Holy Mother of <hi>Jesus,</hi> as to reduce the whole Design of the Worship of Saints to a <hi>bare Admiration, Commemoration, and Imitation of their Virtues;</hi> as if the Veneration of the Saints, and our Mediation of Intercession,
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:65623:4"/> directed mediately or immediately unto<note place="margin">Pag. 14.</note> them, were not in themselves <hi>Christian Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> or that the Practice of these Vertues were not due by us, to their high rank, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only way to be revenged on this unreasonable and fearful <hi>Trimmer</hi> (that I can think of) will be to prove in any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable manner the truth of the foregoing Period; and the least that he can do, will be to break his <hi>Speculum</hi> all to pieces; it may be something else.</p>
            <p>And next, for that other open <hi>Vigilantian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apol. p. 16.</note> to come and thank you civilly for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing, in <hi>English, &amp; Permissu Superiorum,</hi> your seasonable Treatise, I think it was nothing but a rude affront, for it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to thank you for Nothing, since nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Design nor Draught was new or singular: <hi>i. e.</hi> the Doctrine and the Practice delivered in your Book, was from all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and Universal; if this were made but good, it wou'd crack the heart-strings of that open <hi>Vigilantian,</hi> which would be a sufficient punishment for his injurious dismembring the very Style of the <hi>Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 18.</note> in a most <hi>weighty Article.</hi> Though, after all, some of your Friends are apt to
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:65623:5"/> think, that the inserting those words [<hi>in the Soul of a pure Creature</hi>] which you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain so much of, for being left out, will make your Cause never the better, if not somewhat worse; for that <hi>Vigilantian</hi> thought it but reasonable to enquire, what greater Titles, what more glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, you could bestow on the Eternal Son of God in our Nature, than you had bestowed on his Virgin-Mother, although but a pure Creature; and the Question, for ought I see, is like to be yet unanswer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And therefore, let us leave these two troublesome people, who seem to have no manner of taste or relish of this kind of Virginal Devotion; and are so wholly taken up with that fanciful way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping one God in simplicity and truth; that I believe if the truth were known they have neither of them in all their lives suffered one <hi>Ecstatick Introversion in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the Grandeurs of Holy</hi> Mary.</p>
            <p>Your Books, Sir, I find, are made up of two parts; 1. <hi>Reasoning. 2. Authority.</hi> For the first, I have nothing to say to it; I believe your Reasons are as good as any that can be brought in defence of such Worship,
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:65623:5"/> and such Practice. And, if I did not think you would take it amiss, I would thank you again and again for that part of your <hi>Apology.</hi> For the <hi>Authoritative</hi> part, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess I am not so well satisfied with it, and it shall be the work of the remainder of this <hi>Epistle,</hi> to shew how little reason you have to be so, in relation to the three or four first Centuries; and here I am in very good earnest, and cannot help expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulating with you, and others your Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Brethren, in the Name both of the Learned and Unlearned of our Nation. Bishop <hi>Bonner</hi> could not allow a Heretick to be a Gentleman; and Card. <hi>Pallavicini</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apparat. cap. 7.</note> says, <hi>that whereas, since the Reformation, there have been a very great number of Catholicks, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly renowned both for their Piety and Learning; the Heresie could not shew even one famous for the first, and not many for the latter.</hi> I'm afraid that a hundred years hence, Hereticks will be born without Noses, and shall not be able so much as to learn to read: But had not rage and fury blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the eyes of that <hi>Jesuit,</hi> he might have found a thousand, and ten thousand too, dear both to God and Men, both for their
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:65623:6"/> Piety and their Learning. It is very well known how quickly that dawning of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the World, about the end of the 15th Century, brought forth the Reformation; and it is as well known, how kind the Daughter has since proved to the Mother. And envy must confess, that <hi>England</hi> has made as great improvements in all Arts and Sciences, and advanced Learning of all kinds, as far as any Nation in the World besides has done. But what is this (you will say) to you? I answer, Very much. It lies upon you very hard, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit your selves either of profound igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in Books, or extreme disingenuity, in imposing spurious, scoundrel, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded Tracts, for genuine and approved. What greater rudeness and affront can you put upon a Nation of so exact a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, so critical a taste, and such abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant reading, as the <hi>English</hi> is, than to think you can foist your wretched stuff upon them, for old authentick Records? But this is your way, and this is your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that if but one ignorant Reader is seduced by these false Authorities, you have gained one; and if you gain none,
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:65623:6"/> you lose nothing; for disingenuous and unfair dealing in the methods of convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is so frequent, that a right <hi>Catholick</hi> stomach never so much as rises at it, much less is in any danger of revolt.</p>
            <p>I am tempted to pursue this Subject somewhat farther; but I will restrain my self, and set about my work immediately, which shall be to shew, that of all the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities you have alledged in defence of your Doctrine, for the three first Ages, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Books from which you have them are confessedly spurious, or exceeding doubtful; or if the Books be genuine, the Citations are nothing to your purpose.</p>
            <p>To begin therefore with the Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the first Age; the Holy Scriptures, which are cited abundantly, are most of them such as prove, what no body denies, as that <hi>Mary</hi> was the Mother of <hi>Jesus,</hi> her<note place="margin">Apol. 90.</note> excellent Faith, admirable Purity, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Humility, perfect Obedience, Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Obsequiousness, Fortitude and Patience, ay, and whatever else you please that is truly excellent, we are ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, tho' sometimes not from the places brought by you: but why should you say
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:65623:7"/> she is stiled the Spouse of the Holy Ghost, because, <hi>Matth. 1. 20. that which is born of her is of the Holy Ghost?</hi> how do the <hi>Evangelists</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ap. 89.</note> recommend to us her fervent practice of <hi>Ecstatick</hi> Prayer, because <hi>Acts 1. 14. These all continued in Prayer and Supplication, with one</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 90.</note>
               <hi>accord, with the Women, and</hi> Mary <hi>the Mother of Jesus and with his brethren?</hi> but how does that submissive resignation of the humble and obedient Maid, <hi>Luke 1. 38. Behold the handmaid of the Lord, be it unto me according to thy Word,</hi> prove the amplitude of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual<note place="margin">P. 91.</note> power of Holy <hi>Mary,</hi> in the Empire of Grace and Divine Favours, suiting to her illustrious Prerogatives, Vertues, and Merits? where is the stupendous efficacy of her single <hi>Fiat,</hi> be it done, in those words? <hi>J. C.</hi> D. D. of the holy Order of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> will tell us; <hi>As God's</hi> Fiat, <hi>in the beginning</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
               <hi>of Nature, was a demonstrative Mark of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Omnipotency, in extracting the whole Fabrick of the World, with all its Moveables and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, out of a meer nothing: So</hi> Mary'<hi>s</hi> Fiat, <hi>in the beginning of Grace, is an evident token of her appropriated plenitude of Power, proportioned to her fulness of Grace, co-operating with the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty source of all goodness, gives a being, with
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:65623:7"/> all connatural parts and perfections, to Jesus.</hi> Commend me to <hi>J. C.</hi> for making the most of a thing: but this it is, to have ones head stuffed with the Conformities of St. <hi>Francis.</hi> Well, but the efficacy of her<note place="margin">Pag. 92.</note> Mediation of Intercession to God, for Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, appears manifestly, in her sollicitous request to <hi>Jesus,</hi> at the Marriage-Feast in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> Joh. 2. 3. <hi>The Mother of Jesus saith unto him, They have no Wine.</hi> Had I been <hi>J. C.</hi> of all places in the whole Bible, I would never have singled out this pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, to shew the efficacy of her Mediation of Intercession, because of the answer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately following, <hi>V. 4. Woman, what have I to do with thee?</hi> Ay, but hold, says <hi>J. C.</hi> Did not our blessed Lord, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> of our protection by Holy <hi>Mary,</hi> and of her effectual mediation to himself for us, give a most ample instance, in his voluntary subjection and obsequiousness to her Commands, from the Age of 12. to 30. <hi>Luke 2. 51. And he went down with them to</hi> Nazareth, <hi>and was subject to them?</hi> Now, to speak the truth, I can see no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in these plain words, and if there be any thing in them extraordinary, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:65623:8"/> as applicable to St. <hi>Joseph,</hi> as the <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Virgin,</hi> and therefore <hi>J. C.</hi> took care to translate them to his purpose, Jesus went down with <hi>Mary,</hi> to <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and was sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>to Her.</hi> But this is no usual fraud of the Adversaries of the Catholick Church<note place="margin">Ap. p. 18.</note> to lop the Sacred Scriptures themselves, thereby to support a drooping Party and Passion; No, not this, to speak of! the Party indeed we have to deal with, does not droop very much, but certainly the Cause does, that wants such supports as these. In the next place, the application of the <hi>44th</hi> (with us the <hi>45th) Psalm</hi> to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> upon the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Athanasius (Serm. de Deipara)</hi> and <hi>Greg. Nazian. (Traged. de Ch. Patiente)</hi> is hardly to be endured, when the literal sence of it is so suitable to the love of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> to his <hi>Egyptian</hi> Lady, and the Mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, to that of our blessed Lord to his Spouse the Church. But if these two pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (of which I shall speak in their proper places) were sufficient to authorize your applying that <hi>Psalm</hi> to the <hi>Virgin,</hi> yet what<note place="margin">P. 93.</note> shall authorize you to construe, <hi>Vultum tuum deprecabuntur,</hi> by, <hi>Shall pay homage to this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:65623:8"/> Mother,</hi> and set it down as the words of the <hi>Psalmist?</hi> nothing that I know of, but <hi>Quidlibet audendi libertas pro Sancta Matre Ecclesia.</hi> And thus I have done my Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations (for I do not pretend to answer or confute the reason of the Authorities al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged here, or elsewhere) on your Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Quotations. And truly if this be the Use that is to be made of it, I think it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable, it should be withholden not from the <hi>Laity</hi> alone, but <hi>Clergy</hi> also.</p>
            <p>The first Authority, purely humane, is<note place="margin">Apolog. 94.</note> the honourable Testimony of St. <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apostle, who stiles her <hi>an Immaculate Virgin,</hi> in these words, <hi>It was necessary that Christ, born of an Immaculate Virgin, should restore that Life Everlasting which all had forfeited.</hi> Here is nothing in this Citation but what we all agree very well in; but the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Piece we think very question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and because it is made use of, upon other occasions, by your Writers, and the <hi>Putney</hi> Convert, I will give you some of the Reasons, for which we think it not authentick. <hi>Sixtus Senensis</hi> says nothing of it, but gives us warning to be cautious in such matters (quoting <hi>Eusebius</hi> for it) as
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:65623:9"/> relate to the Acts and Passions of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, and says that in the Acts of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</hi> there are abundance of ridiculous stories, about <hi>Egeas,</hi> and <hi>Maximilla,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Possevin</hi> and <hi>Bellarmin</hi> think there is all the reason in the World to believe the <hi>Passion of</hi> St. <hi>Andrew</hi> genuine; <hi>1st.</hi> Because no body had questioned it. And how should they, when it had not long been made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, by the Translation of Cardinal <hi>Sirlet, Gentian Hervet,</hi> and another, from the <hi>Greek</hi> of <hi>Simeon Metaphrastes,</hi> at the request of <hi>Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomannus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Verona,</hi> from whom <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> took it? 2. Because it has nothing of Novelty in it. If the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> will let <hi>Sp. Sanctum, procedentem ex Patre, in filio permanentem,</hi> pass for the Doctrine of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</hi> I have nothing to answer. Let them chuse which they please; for that of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martyrolog. 30 Nov.</note> saying it had lately crept into some Copies, and was not in a great many others, will not go far with us, barely upon his credit. 3. Because the famous Hymn, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve Sancta Crux,</hi> was undoubtedly taken from this Passion of St. <hi>Andrew.</hi> That it might very well be, and yet the <hi>Passio S. And.</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the more genuine, unless it could be
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:65623:9"/> proved, that this <hi>Hymn</hi> were 15 or 16 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years old. 4. Because <hi>Johannes a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanio, Aloysius Lipomanus,</hi> and the Correctors of the <hi>Roman Breviary,</hi> think it a very ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Piece. To this <hi>Bellarmin</hi> shall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, namely, that he knew <hi>a great Man,</hi> (that will go for two sure) that call'd this Passion in question: and farther, that it was very vigorously disputed by grave and learned Men, before it could pass. 5. <hi>Petrus Damiani,</hi> (who died 1072.) and St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> in a Sermon on the Vigil and Feast of St. <hi>And▪</hi> (which <hi>Labbe</hi> knows not if it be his or no) cite this Piece as authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. We have nothing to say to this, but that it might pass for true in the days of St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and before. But the Question is, If it be the Presbyters of <hi>Achaia,</hi> as is pretended. To the Reasons aforemention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Labbeus</hi> adds the auxiliary forces of hard words, and vile injurious reproaches on the <hi>Protestant</hi> Authors that had exposed this Piece as spurious, and indeed it is all the Arguments that he has brought, both in this and other Points, against their Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. And whoever shall turn over that <hi>Jesuits</hi> Books, cannot chuse being concerned
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:65623:10"/> to find a man of his laborious industry and learning, so agitated by the rabid Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his Order, as to pass all bounds of moderation, and good manners, towards men of learning, though differing from him in their judgment. We are more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to <hi>Monsieur du Pin,</hi> a late <hi>French Author,</hi> both for his candor and good nature, whose words I will set down at full concerning this present Matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Opinions are divided about the Acts of the Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nouvelle Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liotheque, p. 47.</note>
               <hi>of St.</hi> Andrew, <hi>written by the Presbyters of</hi> Achaia, <hi>which are in</hi> Surius'<hi>s History of the Saints,</hi> Nov. 30. Baronius, Bellarmin, <hi>and some other Catholick Criticks receive them, but a great many more reject them. The Ancients knew no other Acts of St.</hi> Andrew, <hi>than such as were corrupted by the</hi> Manichees, <hi>of which St.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin, Philastrius, <hi>and Pope</hi> Innocent <hi>the first make mention, and which</hi> Gelasius <hi>puts into the number of Apocryphal Books:</hi> But it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,<note place="margin">Du Pin, 47.</note> that those were not the same with these we are now speaking of; and it is yet as certain that these latter Acts of the Passion of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> were never cited by any that lived before the <hi>7th</hi> or <hi>8th Century.</hi> Such as <hi>Remigius Autissiodorensis,</hi> who died
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:65623:10"/> about 900. <hi>Petrus Damiani, 1072. Lanfranc,</hi> St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and <hi>Ivo</hi> of <hi>Chartres.</hi> By which we see we cannot be assured of the truth of it. Thirdly, Not only the Mystery of<note place="margin">P. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Trinity is explained in these Acts, in such a manner as we may well suspect they were made since the Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> but they also teach the error of the latter <hi>Greeks</hi> concerning the Holy Ghost, saying he proceeds from the Father, and abides in the Son. I know it is pretended, that there are <hi>Manuscripts</hi> in which this passage is not found, but who can tell whether these passages were not rather blotted or left out of some Copies, than added or put into others. And therefore this Passion ought at least to be looked upon as a doubtful thing, and such as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> says we may not make any use of, to prove any matter of Faith. Thus far that learned person, and we thank him for his ingenuity. And has <hi>J. C.</hi> D. D. or any of his Writing Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, any thing material to say to all this? when they have, let them quote, <hi>Aloys. Lipom. e Presb. Achaiae</hi> again, but not before. But setting aside the Authority of these learned people, let any ingenuous,
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:65623:11"/> any uninfected man, set himself to read this Piece, and if he do not find enough to make him suspect it, I am very much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken; there he will find <hi>Egeas</hi> telling<note place="margin">Surius, Nov. 30.</note> St. <hi>Andrew</hi> how the <hi>Principes Romani,</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperors had ordered the <hi>Christian</hi> Religion to be rooted out. After great disputes, <hi>Egeas</hi> puts <hi>Andrew</hi> in Prison, but upon the hearing of it, all the People of the Province come to the Apostle, and would have broken up his Prison, and freed him, and were hardly restrained by St. <hi>Andrew</hi> from going presently to kill <hi>Egeas;</hi> but he preached a Sermon of <hi>Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Obedience</hi> (for which I don't find they laugh'd at him) to the people, and so the Pro-Consul escaped. Amongst other things, St. <hi>Andrew</hi> tells <hi>Egeas,</hi> that <hi>Christ</hi> had sent him to that Province, where he had converted a mighty number of people from idolatry. Ay, says <hi>Egeas,</hi> I know you have; there is not a City in all <hi>Achaia</hi> whose Temples are not quite forsaken and empty since your preaching: and therefore I'll make you sacrifice first, that all who have been seduced by you, may return to their old Worship. Is there
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:65623:11"/> any thing likely in all this? Did the people use to gather together so early in defence of Christianity, against their own Governors? Were not the Christians the hate and scorn of all the World? Were not the Judges and Governors forced to restrain the rage of the common people, in their prosecutions of the poor Saints? and how come all things so mightily changed in <hi>Achaia?</hi> that all the <hi>Heathen</hi> Temples should in a manner be quite deserted in so little a time, will not easily be believed, by any who understand the state of those times. After St. <hi>Andrew</hi> had hung upon the Cross two days, <hi>Egeas</hi> came, at the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of his own Brother <hi>Stratocles,</hi> and 20000 followers, to take him down; but the good Apostle prayed to <hi>Christ,</hi> that they might not be able to do it, and as many as stretched out their arms to try, <hi>stupebant,</hi> and could not.</p>
            <p>What follows, seems to me, to be done purely in imitation of <hi>Joseph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> and is thus: How a certain woman, called <hi>Maximilla,</hi> an honourable person, (<hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix,</hi> to answer to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>▪ <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 50.) a chaste and holy Matron, (to answer to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph,</hi>
               <pb n="xx" facs="tcp:65623:12"/> a just and honourable man) as soon as she knew the Apostle was dead, came to the Cross, and with all reverence, took down the Body of the Apostle, and buried it with Spices and Oyntments, and laid him in a Sepulcher, which she had prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for herself. At this <hi>Egeas</hi> was in burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrath, and ordering a Bill of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint (an Indictment of Riot, against the Peace of his Sovereign Lord) to be drawn up to the Emperor, against <hi>Maximilla,</hi> and 20000 of the People, was, in the midst of his anger, caught up by the Devil into the Air, and thrown down headlong into the midst of the <hi>forum,</hi> and died presently. Whose Estate his Brother <hi>Stratocles</hi> would never touch, because his Brother had pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted it with killing the Apostle. These things were done in <hi>Patrae</hi> of <hi>Achaia, Ʋbi praestantur adhuc gloriosa ejus beneficia, us{que} in praesentem diem.</hi> And this Example so terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied all the Country, that they turned Christians immediately. I hope our <hi>English</hi> Missionaries, after this, will be so ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to lay aside the Passion of St. <hi>Andrew.</hi> Your next Authority is fetch'd from S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Liturgy, of which <hi>Sixtus Senensis, Posse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus,</hi>
               <pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:65623:12"/> and <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> say not one word; and <hi>Labbeus</hi> says enough to let you see he is persuaded it is none of his; and thinks it so plain, that there is no need of consult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Protestant</hi> Criticks for Arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, but I would not have the Reader think he calls them <hi>Protestant</hi> Criticks; no, <hi>Allophylos bacchantes consulere, Profanos Criticos, Alastoras Haereticos, Beelzebub Deum Accaron con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultum ire,</hi> are the best words they can get from him. But let us hear what Card. <hi>Bona</hi> says on this matter, <hi>Rer. Liturg. l. 1. c.</hi> 8. About the end of the last <hi>Century, Gulielmus Lindanus,</hi> from Card. <hi>Sirlet</hi>'s Copy, put out the Liturgy of S. <hi>Peter, Gr.</hi> and <hi>Lat.</hi> with a learned Apology for it: but whoever shall read it carefully, will, with me, confess, that nothing can be concluded hence, but that <hi>Peter,</hi> by word of mouth, or writing, delivered a Liturgy to the Church of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> first, and then to that of <hi>Rome:</hi> but that this (which he says <hi>Sirlet</hi> found in <hi>Apulia</hi>) should be it, he by no means proves; and no body will believe it who can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish truth, from falshood; For if this were S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Liturgy indeed, how comes it to pass, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which
<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:65623:13"/> amidst so many storms of Persecution, hath carefully preserved his Relicks, and Epistles, should yet neglect this noble <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mula</hi> of Sacrificing? how comes it, there was nothing seen of it for 1500 and more years, in the <hi>Catholick</hi> Writings? and thus that Cardinal goes on at a mighty rate, but because the afore-mentioned <hi>Ellies du Pin,</hi> Doctor of the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> and at present in great repute with the Church of <hi>France,</hi> hath dispatch'd this business effectually, and made use of Card. <hi>Bona</hi>'s Arguments, and because I find I grow tedious, I will take leave to translate a <hi>short Chapter</hi> of his, which will give you full satisfaction in the point of Liturgies, and will also be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to your third Citation out of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy of S. <hi>James, Minor.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Liturgies falsly attributed to the Apostles, <hi>Page 21.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We need only to reflect a little on the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nouvelle Bibl.</note>
                  <hi>of the Eucharist in S.</hi> Paul'<hi>s Epistle to the</hi> Corinthians, <hi>and on what</hi> Just. Martyr, <hi>and others of the first Ecclesiastick Writers have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered down on that Subject, to be persuaded that the Apostles and their Successors celebrated the
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:65623:13"/> Sacrifice of the Mass, with great simplicity. This is what has been observed by all who have written on the Liturgies, who agree, that Mass was, in the first days, performed without much Ceremony, and a very few Prayers made use of; but that by little and little both Prayers and Ceremonies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased, to conciliate the greater reverence to the Sacrifice. At last the Churches ordered and set down in Writing, the manner of Celebrating, which was called the Liturgy. And the reason of their differing, proceeded from their conforming to the several Ʋsages and Customs of several places. And because men are naturally carried to change something in their exterior part of Worship, there have therefore many things been added from time to time to these Liturgies.</hi> This Remark alone, may suffice to let you see, that the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies which carry the Apostles names, and Evangelists, are truly none of theirs; but to prove it invincibly, we need only exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them one after another.</p>
               <p>The Liturgy, or <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Mass, attributed to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and published by <hi>Lindanus,</hi> 1589. from Card. <hi>Sirlet</hi>'s <hi>MS.</hi> which was not very old, and which has since been printed at <hi>Paris</hi> by <hi>Morellius,</hi> 1595. cannot be S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, for the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="xxiv" facs="tcp:65623:14"/> reasons. There is mention made of S. <hi>Sixtus, Cornelius,</hi> and S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> (the last of which died 258). The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is there called the Mother of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a term which was not in common use be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the condemnation of <hi>Nestorius.</hi> [Card. <hi>Bona</hi> in his Defence of S. <hi>James</hi>'s Liturgy, quotes <hi>Evagrius,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret</hi> confessing that the ancient Fathers both called the blessed Virgin <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and believed her to be so. But certainly S. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who was present at, and a great part of the Church of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> in 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1, did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Apostles S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>James</hi> to have ever called her so, when he says in his Epistle, about the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The admirable Disciples have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us down this Faith, though they have not made mention of the word or term <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Therefore S. <hi>Cyril</hi> did not know of any Liturgy of S. <hi>Peter</hi> or S. <hi>James,</hi> where <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is mentioned. But this by the way, and now to <hi>Du Pin</hi> again.] The Canon of the <hi>Latin</hi> Mass, which S. <hi>Gregory</hi> says was made by a <hi>Scholasticus, i. e.</hi> a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man, of the <hi>fifth Century,</hi> is there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:65623:14"/> entire: besides, it has Prayers in it, taken out of <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Sacramentary, S. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil</hi>'s, and S. <hi>Chrysostom</hi>'s Liturgies. There they pray for the <hi>Patriarch,</hi> a term not known before the end of the <hi>fourth Century,</hi> and for the most Religious Emperors. In a word, had this Liturgy been S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would have made use of it, and it could not have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known for so many Ages. These reasons made the learned Card. <hi>Bona</hi> say this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy was spurious, and had certainly been composed by some <hi>Greek</hi> Priest lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, because it was taken partly from the <hi>Greek</hi> and partly from the <hi>Latin</hi> Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and then was christened S. <hi>Peters,</hi> either to gain it more Authority, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it contained a great part of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Liturgy.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ethiopick</hi> Liturgy, that bears the Name of S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> is visibly supposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious; there they pray for the <hi>Popes,</hi> for <hi>Kings,</hi> for <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> and <hi>Arch-bishops;</hi> the <hi>twelve Apostles</hi> are there invoked; there they mention the <hi>four Evangelists;</hi> speak of the Synods of <hi>Nice, Constantinople,</hi> and <hi>Ephesus;</hi> there they sing the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:65623:15"/> with the Particle <hi>Filioque;</hi> there they men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Athanasius, Basil,</hi> and S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> the <hi>Epact; Golden Number,</hi> and <hi>Trisagion,</hi> by which we see this Liturgy was of latter date.</p>
               <p>There remains no more but the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy attributed to S. <hi>James,</hi> which Men of Learning have taken pains to defend, but to no purpose; for though it be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienter, than those we have examined, since it is cited by the Council in <hi>Trullo,</hi> after the fifth General Council, [held ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Petavius,</hi> 707.] Yet however, we cannot say, that S. <hi>James</hi> was the Author, or that it was made in his time. For, <hi>1st.</hi> the Virgin is in this Liturgy call'd the <hi>Mother of God;</hi> the Son and Holy Ghost are said to be Consubstantial with the Father; terms which were not in use in S. <hi>James</hi>'s time, for if they had, is it credible, that this Authority would not have been alledged in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils of <hi>Nice, Ephesus,</hi> and <hi>Constantinople?</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. We find here the <hi>Trisagion,</hi> and the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Patri,</hi> which were not commonly used in the Church, till the <hi>5th Century;</hi> for though you should prove they were used
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:65623:15"/> before, yet you must own, that it was not the common custom of the Church so to do. 3. There they pray for such as were shut up in Monasteries; but who can say there were Monasteries in S. <hi>James</hi>'s time? 4. There is mention made of <hi>Confessors,</hi> a term not used in the Divine Offices till a great while after S. <hi>James,</hi> even in Card. <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s own judgment. 5. This Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy speaks of <hi>Temples,</hi> and <hi>Incensing of Altars,</hi> and does any one believe, there were such things so early? 6. The whole Liturgy is full of Citations out of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epistles, most of which were written after the death of S. <hi>James.</hi> And one cannot fairly say with Card. <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and <hi>Bona</hi> [and <hi>Labbe</hi>] that these things were added to S. <hi>James</hi>'s Liturgy; because there is no manner of likelyhood, people should add so many passages; and besides, the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies throughout the whole, do by no means agree with the Apostles days. Thus far <hi>du Pin,</hi> and I hope you will either cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit or confute him. I durst not for my life venture any Authors with you, but genuine <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and therefore I have not so much as looked on <hi>Perkins, Cooke, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet,
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:65623:16"/> Aubertin, Blondel,</hi> or <hi>Daille,</hi> with several others, for fear you should apprehend any foul play.</p>
               <p>And now I leave you and your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to consider on the Liturgies, and pass to your last Citation out of <hi>Dionysius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite;</hi> not that I intend any thing against the words, but to let you see how little reason you have to believe those Books which pass under <hi>Denis</hi> his Name, to be his, notwithstanding you have a great many learned Men on your side. <hi>Sixtus Senensis,</hi> and <hi>Possevinus,</hi> are positive in the point, and so is <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> although the first acknowledges that Cardinal <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetan,</hi> and the third <hi>Constantine</hi> Council, believed otherwise, and the latter, that <hi>Valla</hi> and <hi>Erasmus [quidam scioli</hi>] thought otherwise; O great <hi>Apollo!</hi> who would not pass for a Dunce, when <hi>Valla</hi> and <hi>Erasmus</hi> pass for Smatterers! But Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Pallavicini, Lib. 1. cap.</hi> 23. has thrown the latter as low as a Man can go, but at the same time he falls himself into the lowest degree of contempt, with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry understanding Reader. <hi>Ph. Labbeus</hi> has, I know not how, obtained of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:65623:16"/> to be indifferent in the case. And <hi>Casimir Oudin,</hi> a late ingenious moderate<note place="margin">Supplement. de Script. Ecc. Paris, 1686.</note> Critick, lays the matter down so fairly and plainly, that though he does not expresly say it, yet you may easily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his opinion of the Book to be, that it is spurious. But <hi>Du Pin</hi> has done the business effectually, and therefore I will not grudge the pains of making an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract of his judgment, from the Reasons following.</p>
               <p>1. The manner of these Books first ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing<note place="margin">Du Pin, p. 90.</note> looks suspicious; they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to all antiquity, and at last pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the <hi>Severiani,</hi> Hereticks, in a Conference held with the <hi>Catholick.</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> in the Emperor's Palace, in Five hundred thirty two, to support their Errors by. But what do the <hi>Catholicks</hi> say to this? How can you shew us, (say they to the Hereticks) that these Testimonies you say are <hi>Dionysius</hi> his, are so indeed? had they been so, they could not have been unknown to blessed <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril.</hi> But why do we mention St. <hi>Cyril;</hi> for if St. <hi>Athanasius</hi> had believed them to be St. <hi>Denis</hi> his, would he not have made
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:65623:17"/> use of that Authority, to prove the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiality of the blessed Trinity, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Blasphemies of <hi>Arius?</hi> but now since none of the Ancients has cited them, how can you prove them to belong to <hi>Dionysius?</hi> thus that Council argued then; but afterwards, finding nothing in the Books repugnant to the Faith, they were admitted for genuine. But <hi>Du Pin</hi> could not find that the Council had taken care to answer their own Arguments and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections. To this he adds, that they are wholly omitted by St. <hi>Jerome</hi> and St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin,</hi> whose purposes they would have served very well, had they known them.</p>
               <p>2. The Style and Method are very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent<note place="margin">Du Pin, 92.</note> from the way of Writing in the first and second Age of the Church. The Style is puft, affected, and unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; the meanest simplest things are am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified extravagantly; the Periods are artificial, and his Reasons ranged in great order, which looks more like a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher, writing at leisure, and with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditation.</p>
               <pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:65623:17"/>
               <p>3. The Subject of these Books does not at all agree with the times of St. <hi>Denis.</hi> The <hi>Christians</hi> in the first Ages were taken up in three sorts of Works, in making Apologies for their Religion, in Letters of Instruction to the Faithful, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them to Martyrdom; and last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in writing against Hereticks. Now the subject and design of <hi>Denis</hi> all along is clear another thing: it is to speak of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries in the most exquisite and curious manner possible, to explain them by <hi>Plato's</hi> Principles, and in the Terms of that School, not to propose them with the simplicity of the Ancients, but to find out all sorts of Difficulties, and answer them; to raise Questions, more nice than useful, concerning the Nature of God, and the different Orders of Angels. He explains the Trinity clearer than <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasius</hi> himself; he rejects dextrously the Errors of the <hi>Nestorians, Eutychians,</hi> and <hi>Anthropomorphites;</hi> he speaks of the Church as flourishing, and in peace, and makes no mention of Martyrs or Persecutions. In the last Chapter of the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> he defends the Baptism of Infants by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:65623:18"/> tradition. We say (says he) here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that which our Bishops (taught by ancient tradition) have delivered down to us. Tradition must needs be very ancient in St. <hi>Denis</hi> his days. He describes the Ceremonies of Solemn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, such as were in use when the Church was freed from Persecutions, with a great deal of pomp. He speaks of Temples built expresly, in which there was a Sanctuary separate from the other parts, of incensing of Altars, and Ceremonies used about the <hi>Energumeni, Catechumeni,</hi> and <hi>Penitents.</hi> He speaks of <hi>Monks,</hi> and describes their way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrating. He dedicates a Book to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> and quotes in it an Epistle of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> now <hi>Timothy</hi> was dead, and <hi>Onesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> in his place, when <hi>Ignatius</hi> wrote his Epistles. He cites and explains the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, and Revelations of St. <hi>John,</hi> as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical and Authentick, which was not received for such (the Revelations that is) for some Ages after; and St. <hi>John</hi> had hardly written them in <hi>Denis</hi> his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time. He quotes the Epistle of <hi>Ignatius</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> written a little before his
<pb n="xxxiii" facs="tcp:65623:18"/> Martyrdom, which was in <hi>Trajan's</hi> time, 108. when all agree that <hi>Denis</hi> himself suffered in <hi>Domitian's</hi> time, unless those who to reconcile this contradiction have lengthened out his days to 109 and 118, without any good grounds; little think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the lower they removed him, so much the nearer they came to the truth. He quotes a Passage out of one <hi>Clement</hi> a Philosopher, which is found in the Eighth Book of <hi>Clemens Alex. Strom.</hi> that lived in the Third Century. I am weary of confirming the spuriousness of <hi>Dionysius.</hi> He who is not satisfied with what is already set down, must read <hi>Du Pin</hi> himself, who has treated this matter so fully, and yet in short, that he has left nothing to doubt of.</p>
               <p>And thus I have dispatched, I think, your honourable Testimonies of the First Age, by shewing, that there is not one of them genuine, and authentick, even in the judgment of Authors of your own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p>Your Testimonies of the Second Age are fetch'd indeed from genuine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, but I will leave any man to
<pb n="xxxiv" facs="tcp:65623:19"/> judge how fairly you have represented them.</p>
               <p>The first is a Passage out of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> which you have given us by halves, and therefore I will set it down at full, as I find it, <hi>Lib. 5. cap.</hi> 19. in a barbarous translation. As the one (<hi>Eve</hi>) was sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, by the words of the Devil (<hi>per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicum sermonem</hi>) to fly from God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicating his word, so the other (<hi>Mary</hi>) was told by an Angel, (<hi>per Angelicum ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem evangelizata</hi>) that she should bear God, obeying his Word; and as the one was seduced to fly from God, so was the other induced to obey God; that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> might become the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of the Virgin <hi>Eve</hi> (not as you have translated it, of the guilty Children of <hi>Eve</hi>) and as Mankind was bound over to death by a Virgin, it might be also by a Virgin loosed: the Virgin-obedience of one being fairly set against the Virgin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disobedience of the other. If <hi>Irenaeus</hi> means to be understood literally, as you seem to think, I should not doubt to say he was grosly mistaken; for it was certainly the obedience of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi>
                  <pb n="xxxv" facs="tcp:65623:19"/> God-Man, alone, that could be fairly set against the disobedience of our first Parents, and by whom our debt was paid, and we set free from the bonds of Everlasting Death; but take the whole parallel in any tolerable sence; and make what you can of <hi>Advocata.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you want any farther satisfaction about this Citation, I refer you to <hi>A Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scourse concerning the Worship of the blessed Virgin, and the Saints,</hi> Printed 1686. where you may find it, as also on your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing one out of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> where you may find the true translation of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> words, set down by you, (<hi>Apol. pag.</hi> 97.) which you seem to be utterly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of.</p>
               <p>Your third Quotation is out of <hi>Justin</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apology for Contempl. p. 97.</note>
                  <hi>Martyr,</hi> where you say (<hi>Apol. pag.</hi> 97.) he doth in express words vindicate this Age of the Church, from the imputation of Atheism, impos'd by Pagans, for the Practice of Saint-Servitude, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the Fact, but denying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing the Crime, in that Christians give them, not Divine, but only Saint-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, <hi>Just. Martyr, Ap.</hi> 2. Good God! that
<pb n="xxxvi" facs="tcp:65623:20"/> ever any reasonable creature should be thus imposed on! the Christians cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Atheists, for practising Saint-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude! acknowledging their Saint-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, but denying it to be a fault! distinguishing betwixt <hi>latreutick,</hi> and <hi>dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leutick Worship!</hi> let me live and die a barbarous Monk, if I know what to say to you; or if I am not ashamed at my heart to confute a D. D. in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter so plain. Had the modern Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Worship prevailed in <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s time, the Christians had never been called or thought Atheists, for many good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. But Sir, when I have given you the true translation of the Passage in <hi>Justin,</hi> I will leave you to the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and correction of your Superiors, if you are ignorant of your mistakes; but if not, to the checks of your own Conscience, and to the punishment you owe to violated Truth and Honesty. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (says the Father) we profess our selves Atheists, with respect to those whom you look upon as Gods; yet not in respect of the true God, the Parent and Fountain of Wisdom and
<pb n="xxxvii" facs="tcp:65623:20"/> Righteousness, and all other Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Perfections, who is infinitely free from the least contagion or spot of Evil. Him, and his only begotten Son, (who came from him and taught these things both to us, and to the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of good Angels, who follow and are conformable to his Will) and the Spirit of Prophecy (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Holy Ghost) we worship and adore, honouring them in Truth, and with the Highest Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are now come to the Testimonies of the Third Age, St. <hi>Cyprian, Eusebius Alexandrinus,</hi> (whom I cannot in all my Catalogues of Authors discover) <hi>Origen,</hi> and <hi>Methodius;</hi> of the three first I shall say nothing, because I think they have said nothing themselves; when their Passages are produced, you may receive satisfaction, but because abundance of your Modern Authors have quoted St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian de Caena Domini,</hi> and think it very ancient at least, as Mr. <hi>Sclater,</hi> and the Convert of late, in <hi>Reason and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> I shall shew you in short, in what esteem it is held by your own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.
<pb n="xxxviii" facs="tcp:65623:21"/>
                  <hi>Bellarmin</hi> disowns it, but will have it an Ancient and Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's. <hi>Labbeus</hi> places it where it should be, with <hi>Arnoldus Abbas Bonaevallis,</hi> who flourished about 1160. O wonderful An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity! a little more than five hundred years old! <hi>Casimir Oudin,</hi> gives him the same place, and so does <hi>Du Pin.</hi> And this is the grave Gentleman that is brought in, to be an Author of the Third Century. Of <hi>Methodius,</hi> the last, but only Testimony of this Age produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in words by you, I have this to inform you, that <hi>Sixtus Sene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sis,</hi> and <hi>Bellarmin</hi> say nothing of this Piece. <hi>Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sevin</hi> likes it well. <hi>Labbe</hi> gives it us in the Edition of <hi>Combesis,</hi> 1644. but passes no judgment on it. <hi>Du Pin</hi> says it was never cited by the Ancients, nor num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred up by <hi>Photius;</hi> but yet has some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of his style, only more swelling, and more full of Epithets; he explains the Mysteries of the Tinity▪ Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Divinity of the Word, (whom he calls Consubstantial to the Father abundance of times) the <hi>Trisagion,</hi> and the Virginity of blessed <hi>Mary</hi> even after
<pb n="xxxix" facs="tcp:65623:21"/> her bringing forth Jesus Christ, and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin, so clearly, that there is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to doubt, if nothing was added to this Serm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n after its first composure. But let us see what Reasons <hi>Casimir Oudin, Pag.</hi> 22. can bring for his fathering this Piece on one <hi>Methodius,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Supplem.</note> in the Year 840.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1st.</hi> This Oration was pronounced in some great Council, or Assembly, where abundance of Bishops were met (whom he calls Honourable Fathers and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) to celebrate that Festival with great joy; which agrees very ill with the times of Persecution, in which <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodius</hi> the Elder lived, under <hi>Diocletian</hi> and <hi>Maximian,</hi> by whom he was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryed, 302 or 303. but all things agree with the times of <hi>Methodius</hi> the Youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>2ly.</hi> The Oration has in it, (speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Christ</hi>) Thou art the True Light, of the True Light, very God, of very God, which plainly alludes to that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, before the making of which <hi>Methodius</hi> was long dead. <hi>3ly.</hi> He plainly falls upon <hi>Nesto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> and confutes his Heresie at every
<pb n="xl" facs="tcp:65623:22"/> turn; he affects on purpose to call often on the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Mother of God;</hi> but <hi>Nestorius</hi> his Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie was condemned an hundred and thirty years after <hi>Methodius</hi> his time. <hi>4ly.</hi> There is so near an affinity between this Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the rest of <hi>Methodius</hi> Junior's Works, that an Egg is not liker an Egg; and <hi>Oudin</hi> instances in some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. <hi>5thly.</hi> The Author thus speaks, Before Thee there was no other God, the Son of God the Father, and after Thee there shall be no other Son <hi>Consub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial</hi> to the Father; which very term argues the Author to have lived after the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, therefore not <hi>Methodius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I finished what I engaged for, as to the Testimonies of the three first Ages, and though I intended to take the Testimonies of the Fourth Age, into some kind of examination also, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I find I have already taken too much liberty, I will ease both you and my self, when I have told you, that St. <hi>Basil</hi> has three Liturgies which go under his Name, and Cardinal <hi>Bona,</hi> says <hi>Goar,</hi> (who wrote learnedly on Liturgies) complains how
<pb n="xli" facs="tcp:65623:22"/> hard it is to discern the genuine and<note place="margin">Bona Rerum. Lit. l. 1. c. 9.</note> true Text of St. <hi>Basil,</hi> from the Additions made by later hands; he says the like also of St. <hi>Chrysostom</hi>'s Liturgy, so that you must not be too confident. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> passes the censure of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness on <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi>'s Tragedy, <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus Patiens,</hi> out of which you had your Quotation, and pray remember it is Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. The Epistle of St. <hi>Hierom. 10. ad Paul. &amp; Eustoch.</hi> is expresly rejected by <hi>Possevin.</hi> The Sermon <hi>de laudibus Mariae,</hi> out of which you cite your Testimony, is rejected by <hi>Petavius,</hi> and <hi>Labbeus,</hi> as none of <hi>Epiphanius</hi>'s. And lastly, the <hi>Sermo de Sanctiss. Deipara</hi> you cite under St. <hi>Athanasius</hi>'s name, is cast by, for abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of reasons given by <hi>Baronius,</hi> and <hi>Bellarmin; Oudin,</hi> shall shut up all. <hi>De San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctissima</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Supplem. p. 32.</note>
                  <hi>Deipara Virgine—Opus de quo dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> Baronius <hi>&amp;</hi> Bellarminus, <hi>sed</hi> Spinel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus <hi>&amp;</hi> Maraccius <hi>fulcire, atque</hi> Athanasio <hi>vindicare conantur; hoc ordinarium est valde Devotis, ut inter extases suas</hi> (Ecstatick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversions) <hi>non habeant gustum: sed indiscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatim omnia approbent satisfacientia suis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taticis excessibus uti hac in parte contigit</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nello
<pb n="xlii" facs="tcp:65623:23"/> &amp; Maraccio (&amp; J. C. D. D.) <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianis Devotis.</hi> All the English I shall give this, is, that it is a <hi>Spec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um</hi> for <hi>J. C.</hi> D. D. of the Holy Order of St. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> made by one <hi>Cafimir Outin,</hi> a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Trimmer.</p>
               <p>And now, since I have been all this while clearing honest Authors of the spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Brats laid to their charge, it is but fit I should let you know, that the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Piece is none of my own, but a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and renowned <hi>French</hi>-man's, which I have drest up in <hi>English,</hi> with some little alteration of the style, and addition of some little matters. If you shall think fit to answer either the <hi>Preface</hi> or the <hi>Book,</hi> you must only clear the Authorities I have been calling into question, and there's an end. For I affure you, I intend to make no other Answer to you than Mr. <hi>W.</hi> of <hi>Oxford</hi> does to his Opponents, <hi>viz.</hi> by tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating <hi>The Conformities of St.</hi> Francis, by honest <hi>Batholomew of Pisa;</hi> and when that's answered, I'll write the Life of Pope <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Sixth, with a Discourse at the end, of the <hi>Continency of the R. Clergy;</hi> and then a Discourse of the Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="xliii" facs="tcp:65623:23"/> under <hi>Donna Olympia,</hi> in which I shall make out, that the Worship or Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration paid to her Brother-in-law, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth, was somewhat more than Saint-servitude.</p>
               <p>Thus, Sir, (beseeching you, in the Name of God, and for the sake of common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity, to propagate no more this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and this Practice, so grievous and afflicting to the Reformed World; and which makes our Holy Religion the Scorn and Scandal of all <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi>) I remain</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:65623:24"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65623:24"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Life and Death</hi> OF THE Blessed Virgin.</head>
            <p>ALL the Service that is paid to the Blessed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, is founded (as they love to speak) upon the greatnesses of <hi>Mary, i. e.</hi> upon the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Privileges she received from God in her <hi>Conception, Birth, Life, Death, Resurrection,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Assumption:</hi> Of these her Greatnesses we find no mention at all in Holy Scripture, and I am persuaded there is some mystery and secret reason of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the silence of the Evangelists, who tell us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Birth, the Life or death of the Mother of Jesus Christ, she appears but in four or five passages of the Gospel, from the birth of our Saviour; and even some of them are such, as make not much for her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65623:25"/> Such, for example, is that which happened at the Marriage in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> where undertaking to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Lord there was no more Wine left to entertain the Guests, she receiv'd an Answer, to our thinking, very hard: <hi>Woman, what have I to do with thee? mine hour is not yet come.</hi> And like to this is that other passage of the Gospel, where she stood without with his Brethren, with purpose he should come and speak with her. But to those who brought the Message, he returned this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, <hi>Who is my Mother, and who are my Brethren?</hi> and went not, that we know of. This does not very well agree with that profound Respect, and reverend manner of Deportment, with which (they say) he treats her now in Heaven. This silence of the <hi>Evangelists,</hi> proceeds, unquestionably, from the same reason, for which it pleased God to conceal the Body of <hi>Moses</hi> heretofore; to wit, that the <hi>Israeletes</hi> might not find it out, and make an Idol of it. So God was pleased the <hi>Evangelists</hi> should say no more of her, than was necessary to teach us the Mystery of the <hi>Incarnation;</hi> that Men might not (with any shew of reason) Father on his word, those horrible Superstitions which he foresaw and knew <hi>Papism</hi> and false Devotion, would one day introduce into the World.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Evangelists</hi> have got nothing by this their Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Birth, the Life and Death of <hi>Mary.</hi> We know them very well without their help. We have divined and discovered all. God knows how, indeed, but so it is, we have a compleat History of the whole. 'Tis true, it is so fabulous, and in some places so shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, that even the Legends of <hi>Latona,</hi> Mother of <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Diana,</hi> or of <hi>Rhea,</hi> called the Mother of the Gods, cannot possibly be more. In the design of making her a Goddess, and allotting her a Worship, very near to that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65623:25"/> we pay to Jesus Christ, there is nothing great and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in the Birth and Death of our Lord, the Son, that <hi>Papism</hi> has forgot to imitate and attribute to the Mother, excepting that they have not dared, as yet, to say, She was conceived of the Holy Ghost. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore see a short Abridgment of this Legend, which the <hi>Greeks</hi> (who were always notable Men at Invention) first began, and to which the <hi>Latins</hi> (scorning to stay behind) put the finishing hand.</p>
            <p>First then, we have happily learn'd, (but you must not ask me how, or from whom,) that the Father of the Blessed Virgin's Name was <hi>Joachim,</hi> who was of the Royal Line, her Mothers, <hi>Ann.</hi> Which <hi>Ann</hi> had two<note place="margin">Baronius in apparatu An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> Sisters, the one called <hi>Mary,</hi> and the other <hi>Soba,</hi> all three Daughters of <hi>Matan</hi> the Priest; for it was neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary that the Royal and the Priestly Line should concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and meet in her, who was to bring forth him, who is our Priest and King. From <hi>Epiphanius</hi>'s time, <hi>Joachim</hi>
               <note place="margin">Haeres. 78. 79.</note> and <hi>Ann,</hi> have gone for the Father and Mother of the Blessed Virgin: But Revelation (like a Snow-ball) still goes on encreasing, and we have found, since <hi>John Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mascene</hi>'s<note place="margin">J. Damascen. 1. 14. de Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. fide. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> time, who lived in the Eighth Century, that this <hi>Joachim</hi> was the Son of one <hi>Barpanther,</hi> who was the Son of <hi>Panther.</hi> 'Tis true, these Names are not usually found among the <hi>Jewish</hi> Genealogies, nor are of <hi>Hebrew</hi> extract; but what was that to <hi>John Damascene,</hi> who neither understood a word of <hi>Hebrew,</hi> nor thought himself oblig'd to such exactness? We are also told, to<note place="margin">Niceph. <hi>lib. 2. cap.</hi> 3.</note> whom the Sisters of this <hi>Ann</hi> were married, and also what Children they had. <hi>Mary,</hi> the Eldest, was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Town of <hi>Rethlehem,</hi> and was the Mother of <hi>Salone</hi> the Midwife. <hi>Soba,</hi> that was the second Sister was the Mother of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Mother of <hi>John Baptist,</hi> and Cousin German to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65623:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ann,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Joachim,</hi> that was to be the Mother of the Mother of the Saviour of the World (the Mother, I say, of her that was to be called our Goddess, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemeress, our Comfortress, (for strange things, you know, must have strange Names) our Advocate, our Refuge, the Salvation of Christians, the Perfection of the Divinity &amp; Trinity) received all manner of Tokens of the future Greatness of the Child she was to bring into the World. She was Barren many years after her Marriage, &amp; because they could not find in whom the fault lay, they were both of them cruelly asham'd; and the High Priest <hi>Isachar</hi> rejected the Offerings of <hi>Joachim,</hi> as of a dry and cursed Tree, saying to him with Indignation, <hi>Cursed is every one that begetteth not a Male Child in Israel. Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> (that understood these things too well, not to know<note place="margin">Pseudo-Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronym. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liod. &amp; Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat.</note> that no such Man as <hi>Isachar</hi> was at that time High Priest, and that they did not use to reject the Offerings of such Men as had barren Wives,) durst not adopt this passage of the story, although he does the rest. But till his time, none ever dar'd to call this History into question, but it went for certain an undoubted truth, upon the pretended Authority of St. <hi>Jerome.</hi> They add farther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, that <hi>Joachim,</hi> covered with confusion for the affront the High Priest had offered him, resolved never to go home again; and that <hi>Ann,</hi> depriv'd of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of her Husband, betook herself to her Prayer, that God would please to send him back, and to take away this her reproach. And hereupon it was, that <hi>Bernardin de</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mariate Part 2. Ser. 3. Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart. de Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meswar. in Stellario l. 1. part. 1. c. 11.</note>
               <hi>Bustis</hi> made that pious and ingenious Application of the words of <hi>Moses,</hi> to <hi>Joachim,</hi> and <hi>Ann. In the beginning God made Heaven and Earth:</hi> By Heaven (says he) we must understand the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the Lady of the World. <hi>And God said, Let there be Light:</hi> That is (says he) Let <hi>Mary</hi> be begotten, and be born. Poor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65623:26"/>
               <hi>Joachim,</hi> overwhelm'd with grief, went and hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in the Wilderness, where continuing forty days in Prayer and Fasting, an Angel at last appeared to him, and promis'd him the Birth of <hi>Mary,</hi> giving him this for a Token, that in going home, he should meet his Wife at a certain Gate of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> called the Gilded Gate. <hi>Ann</hi> at the same time pouring forth her Prayers and Tears, was got into the Holy of Holies, to get as near as she could to the Throne of God. Indeed, no Woman yet had enter'd into that Sacred Place, and even among Men, it was the privilege of the High Priest alone to do it, and that but once a Year, on the great Feast of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiations.</hi> But what might not shee do, who was to be the Mother of the Virgin? And who should have dar'd to shut the door against her? Hither then the Angel came, and declar'd to her the Birth of <hi>Mary,</hi> and order'd her to go and meet her Husband in such a place: It was the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> that perform'd this Office, as <hi>Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din de Bustis,</hi> and <hi>Batholomew</hi> of <hi>Pisa,</hi> Authors of sovereign and unquestionable Authority, both assure us: Who add moreover, That he received this Commission of God with Joy incredible; and that returning into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the whole Quire of Angels set themselves to Dance and Sing for Joy, having learned of him the approaching Birth of <hi>Mary,</hi> who was to be their Queen.</p>
            <p>Hitherto the Virgin, and our Lord, are on the square, each of their Births annunciated by an Angel. Her Conception, in the next place, was alike Miraculous; for, (besides that <hi>Joachim</hi> and <hi>Ann,</hi> were both of them past the age of having Children) it was <hi>Immaculate,</hi> i. e. <hi>Mary</hi> also, as well as <hi>Jesus,</hi> was Conceived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Original Sin. The Church knew nothing of this Mystery, for Eleven or Twelve hundred Years, when certain lazy Canons of <hi>Lyons</hi> set themselves to invent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65623:27"/> this Fancy, whom St. <hi>Bernard</hi> labour'd to Confound,<note place="margin">Ep. 174. ad Can. Lugd.</note> but without any great success. The devotion to the Virgin daily increasing, it was found very convenient She should be exempted from the Law, common to all the Children of <hi>Adam.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, that all the Fathers, St. <hi>Augustine, Ambrose, Chrysostome, Remigius,</hi> and the rest, were of another opinion, as <hi>Melchior Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> the Learned Bishop of the <hi>Canaries,</hi> proves, from their Citations: But we are to appeal, it seems, from them, as incompetent Judges in this Case, though their Authority be very good in any other. The Jesuite <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Eq. ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. cap. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Disput. 51.</note> does all he can, to Invalidate their Testimony and Authority. He says, That Proofs drawn from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, are not altogether sure: That the greatest part of Fathers, cited against the Immaculate Conception, deserve not to be heard; and that, at last however, God had not revealed all things to all Men: That the Fathers were Ignorant of this great truth, the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which was reserved for these latter Ages of the World.</p>
            <p>This is no place to give you an account of the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bickerings there have been, upon this score, for many Ages, and even in this of ours, between the <hi>Jacobins,</hi> and <hi>Cordeliers,</hi> i. e. <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciscans.</hi> The former maintaining, with <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> that the Virgin was conceived in Original Sin: The latter, with <hi>Scotus,</hi> that She was conceived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. And although the Popes have never formally and in express words, decreed it to be an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> yet they have defined it as a <hi>Truth,</hi> which no Man can oppose without great Rashness. And it has been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> to Preach, deliver their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Teach in publick or private, directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, any thing against the Immaculate Conception of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65623:27"/> the Virgin, since which the worship of Her has exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly encreased; every Body almost hath chosen Her for their Patroness, and whole Kingdoms have put themselves into <hi>Her Protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is this a place to refute this Extravagance in, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it very well deserves to be refuted, since it smells strongly of Profaneness, in that it deprives our Saviour of the Honour and Advantage of having been the only <hi>One</hi> that was Conceived without Sin; and of being the Redeemer of the World without Exception. For if the Blessed Virgin was without both Actual, and Original Sin, I do not see how She stood in need of either Remission, or Redemption, and She contributed nothing to Her self, or to Her own Salvation, by bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Jesus Christ into the World.</p>
            <p>We must not here forget, that <hi>Papism,</hi> agreable to the spirit of Error by which it stands, has not failed to heap Fable upon Fable, and to establish this Immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Conception, by many a lying Miracle, and many a false Vision. Saint <hi>Briget</hi> has defin'd this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie many a time and oft, and the Virgin Mother has revealed it to her frequently, that She was Conceived without Original Sin, and many Miracles have been wrought to that purpose. But that which is as pretty, is, that the <hi>Dominicans</hi> have also had their Saint and<note place="margin">5 Book. Rev. the 13. and Book 6. cap. 49. Tom. 2. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pusc. Tract. 31. c. 5.</note> Prophetess, to maintain She was conceived in Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin, and that was <hi>Catharine</hi> of <hi>Siena,</hi> whose Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is upheld by Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> as much more Creditable than that of <hi>Briget;</hi> for that <hi>Catharine</hi> had been Canonized in due and formal manner, when there was a lawful Pope, and so acknowledged over all the World, whereas <hi>Briget</hi> was Canoniz'd by <hi>Benet</hi> the IX.<note place="margin">Pius the II.</note> in a time of Schism, when no body kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> who was the true Pope, or whether there was any such at all.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:65623:28"/>
            <p>The <hi>Dominicans</hi> not contented with St. <hi>Catharine</hi>'s Revelation, would also have some Miracles to establish their Opinion on; and I believe there are few in the<note place="margin">1507.</note> World, that have not heard of the famous History of the <hi>Dominicans</hi> of <hi>Bearn,</hi> (and here in <hi>England,</hi> by the name of the History of <hi>Jetser</hi>) who took upon them to prove by Miracles, the Conception of the Virgin, to have been in Sin, against the <hi>Cordeliers.</hi> Four of these Men, undertook to deceive and cheat a wretched simple Novice of their Convent; and one of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him like a Spirit, telling him, that the Order of <hi>Dominicans</hi> was most unjustly hated, because it taught after St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was Conceived in Original Sin: but that their Enemies the <hi>Franciscans,</hi> were sufficiently tormented in Purgatory, and especially among the rest, <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales,</hi> and <hi>John Duns Scotus,</hi> for teaching the contrary: The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> her self in like manner appeared to him, (that is to say, a Fryar in her Habit) and Imprinted on his Right Hand (by way of Vision) one of the Wounds of our Lord, her Son, which the Monk (without a Vision) did really and indeed feel, to his very great pain; and very well he might, for the Virgin-Monk had pierced his Hand through with a great Nail. But in wounding him She gave him some Lint, and Rags made of our Saviours Swadling-bands whilst they abode in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and assured him from her own self, that She was Born in Original Sin. But the Monks, not satisfied with this, gave to our young Novice, (who was indeed a very stupid Block-head) a mighty strong sleeping Potion, which deprived him of all manner of Sense, and Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in this Fit, imprinted other four Wounds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Feet, his Hand and Side, with <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> to imitate the Wounds of our Saviour, and the Marks of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65623:28"/> St. <hi>Francis.</hi> Being come to himself, they made him believe, he had been in an Extasie, during which the Blessed Spirit had imprinted on him these four new Wounds. They gave him also very frequently strange Drinks to make him Foam, and struggle against Death, as Jesus Christ had done before him. Hitherto the poor Wretch had never doubted of the truth of all this, but believed in good earnest, that he had had true Visions from Heaven, and Apparitions of the Virgin. But now at last, began to suspect there must be some En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, Witchcraft, and Illusion in the case; and therefore (after he had been thus Martyr'd several Months) makes his escape from the Convent, to the Magistrates, where he discovered all the Mystery. <hi>Langius</hi> a Monk, in his Chronicle, in the Year 1509. adds, That they made an Image of the Virgin, and fill'd the Head of it with some red Liquor, which distil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the Eyes, She was reputed thereby to weep Blood. They coloured also an Host with Vermilion, and Flesh-colour, as though it had been turned into Flesh; and all this to persuade the World, their Doctrine of the Conception, was true. Four of the <hi>Dominicans</hi> were hereupon seised, <hi>Francis Vulchi,</hi> that counterfeited the Spirit; <hi>Stephen Boltzhorst</hi> Preacher, whose Office was to vent these Visions in the Pulpit, with <hi>J. Vetter,</hi> Prior of the House, and <hi>H. Stenieker,</hi> Receiver; who were all Burnt over against the Convent, in the Year aforesaid. This Story did not serve a little, towards the disabusing of the <hi>Switzers,</hi> some time after, when they reform'd themselves, in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>The Monks, to whom Heaven, in these latter days, revealed the notable Circumstance of the Immaculate Conception, have also, by the same Spirit of Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, learnt the very day when it was. It was on the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65623:29"/> eighth of <hi>December,</hi> and She was brought forth the<note place="margin">Her Birth.</note> eighth of <hi>September</hi> following; this we know, because we know what Age the Virgin was of when She lay Inn of our Saviour: And knowing precisely the Year of our Lord, we know also the Year of his Mothers Birth. Not that the Gospel says a letter of her Age, but that's all one. We have found it in <hi>Nicephorus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 2. c. 2. ex Enodo Antiochedo.</note>
               <hi>Callistus,</hi> an Author that may compare with any Legen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary in the World, and who, by consequence, shall have as much Credit as a true Evangelist. We have found, I say, in this Historian, that the Virgin was just Fifteen, when She brought forth Jesus Christ. She was Born at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> in <hi>Joachims</hi> own House, that stood pretty near to the Pool of <hi>Bethesda,</hi> of which St. <hi>John,</hi> in the <hi>5th.</hi> of his Gospel makes mention. For so says our old Friend, <hi>J. Damascen,</hi> who was Sainted<note place="margin">L. 4. c. 5. de Orth. fide &amp; Orat. 1. de Nat. Virg.</note> for having been a Martyr for the Worship of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins Images. Others (and <hi>Tostatus</hi> for one, on <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.) say, She was Born at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> or <hi>Seppharo,</hi> Three Leagues from thence; but where ever it was, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the whole Universe was moved at it: The Angels (as they did some time after for the Son) De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended in Troops from Heaven, chanting out Hymns, and most Melodious Songs, in honour of the Spouse of their Eternal King. The little holy Maid her self, (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the use of her Reason as soon as She was Born) found also mighty Consolation, and exceeding great Pleasure in it. And, which is a greater Wonder yet,<note place="margin">Pelbart Stel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larium lib. 5. part. 1. art. 3.</note> this Heavenly Melody is every Year repeated, on the same day. And by this Musick, the day of her Birth, which had long been undiscovered, came to be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to a very Contemplative Saint, who had heard this Musick every <hi>8th.</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> and wondered what the matter was; (as a Wiser Man than he, might very
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65623:29"/> well do) and therefore on a time, in one of his Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Fits, begged of God, that he would reveal this matter to him; and was answered, that on this day, the Glorious Virgin was Born; and thus has the Mother gotten the start of her Son. She was even with him, in having Armies of Coelestial Spirits to celebrate the day of her Birth; but this yearly Repetition of the Angels Harmony, has given Her the advantage: For I don't know any Book that says, they do as much for <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be, some Devoto of the Virgin, jealous of the glory of his Queen, may find something less in the Birth of <hi>Mary,</hi> than in that of Jesus Christ, because he hears of no new Star, that accompanied her Birth, as one did his. But this only serves to betray his want of reading; for had he seen but one <hi>Theophilus,</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Historian (of whose Age and Authority, it would be to no purpose to inquire, for no body can give you an account, but however of very good Credit in this Case); he could have told him, that on the Birth-day of the Virgin, the Light of the Sun was doubled; that the Moon received such an augmentation of Light, that she seem'd almost to equalize the Sun, so that the little Cloud that is wont to obscure her, disappeared on the night of this Nativity; and round her Globe shone (as it were) a great Star, of an extraordinary Fire, and Lustre.</p>
            <p>I think, this was another kind of Star, than that which appeared to the Wise Men in the <hi>East,</hi> which seemed to be but a pittiful flying Meteor in the Air, in comparison with this. An Angel gave the Name of <hi>Jesus</hi> before the Child was born, and an Angel did as much for Her, and the name of <hi>Mary</hi> was of Heavens choyce; and it was also Mystical as well as that of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65623:30"/>
               <hi>Jesus,</hi> for <hi>Mary,</hi> or <hi>Miriam,</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> signifies the <hi>Star of the Sea.</hi> Not that any <hi>Jew,</hi> or <hi>Rabbi,</hi> how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found soever, ever understood this <hi>Etymology,</hi> but that it was revealed to our Legendaries so to signifie; that by vertue of it, she might succeed to <hi>Venus,</hi> who was the Morning Star before, and President of the Sea, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a kind of right thereto, by Her extraction from the <hi>Froth</hi> of it: For, as <hi>Salmeron</hi> the Jesuite says, as<note place="margin">Tome 3. Tract. 4.</note> the Star that is called <hi>Hesperus,</hi> and <hi>Lucifer,</hi> directs and conducts the Sailers to the Port, so the Mother of <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah</hi> succours us in all our Dangers, that we may arrive at the Port of the Grace of God, and Life Eternal. Common Seamen have another kind of opinion of her Power, in respect of Ports and Havens, in this World too.</p>
            <p>After the Birth, next comes her Education in her<note place="margin">Niceph. l. 1. cap. 7. Damasc. ubi supra. Cermanes Const. in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comio B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis.</note> tenderest years, the Scriptures say nothing of this nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but we have lost nothing by that, for we learn elsewhere. That <hi>Ann,</hi> to obtain her of God, had, as <hi>Hannah</hi> heretofore had done for <hi>Saemuel,</hi> vowed her to his Service: And that when she was weaned and three Years old, she was presented to the High Priest, who received her as a precious Jewel, and Lodged her in the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> where before stood the <hi>Ark of the Covenant,</hi> and where he himself alone had right to enter, once a Year. <hi>Zachary,</hi> the Father of St. <hi>John Baptist,</hi> was (it seems) High Priest, and made no such unnecessary Scruple as these, How should I intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a little Girl, into a place where I my self can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in but once a year? How can I, in the most sacred and august Partition of the Temple, bring in a Bed, a Nurse, and little Child, with all that's necessary in such a case? And what shall become of all the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities inseparable from the Infant Age? But being a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65623:30"/> Prophet, and knowing the Mystery of all, he received her without any stickling. Thither she was brought accompanied with troops of Virgins with flaming Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in their hands, and there was brought up for eleven years, the Angels all the while supplying her with nourishment. After eleven years, the Priests assembled to consult what they should do with this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Virgin, and at last concluded, to commit her to the Guardianship of St. <hi>Joseph,</hi> of whose vertue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence they were very well assured. 11 and 3 make 14, and at 14 she was affianc'd to <hi>Joseph;</hi> 3 months after, the Angel came with the Salutation, she conceived of the Holy Ghost, and was brought to bed at 15.</p>
            <p>An unbelieving <hi>Jew,</hi> would make a great many odd exceptions to this History, he would say it was a thing unheard of in the Mystery of Religion, to introduce, to feed and bring up a Girl in the <hi>Holy of Holies,</hi> where ordinary Priests themselves durst never enter. He would tell us that Women, were they never so pure, were never admitted into the Temple beyond the place called the Womens Court. He would say, it was very strange the <hi>Rabbins</hi> and ancient Doctors should mention no such thing as this, either to recount or refute it. He would add moreover, that in the Catalogue of High Priests, he could find no such Man as <hi>Zachary,</hi> the Father of <hi>John Baptist.</hi> Indeed, these difficulties have put our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick<note place="margin">Costerus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. 3. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent. Virg.</note> Doctors to no small trouble; and now they rather chuse to say, that round the Sanctuary there were little Chambers, where Recluses and Religious Maids were bred up, and worked for the Temple, to whose care the Education of little <hi>Mary</hi> was intrusted: But our old devout Gentlemen heretofore, never concernod them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with any Scruples or Objections of Unbelievers, but in great simplicity swallowed all for truth, upon the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65623:31"/> word and authority of Saints, such as <hi>J. Damasc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, and consequently made Infallible, at least by the tacit consent of the Church. And who can forbear belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a History that has gotten some twelve hundred years upon his head? For <hi>Gregory Nyssen</hi> reports this: And<note place="margin">In Natalib. Chr. tom. 3.</note> though he reports it only as an <hi>Apocryphal</hi> History, yet the Church has since made it as good as <hi>Canonical,</hi> by an universal Belief of it.</p>
            <p>The Blessed Virgin consented to live with <hi>Joseph,</hi> in shew of Marriage, but in effect, in pure Virginity, for she told him secretly, that she had made a Vow of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stity, and withal advis'd him to do so too. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing her Vow, which seem'd to determine her ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to become a Mother, she quickly after became so, by the operation of the Holy Ghost. And here, the Doctors are in great trouble to know, of what it was, that the Virgin conceived, and formed the Saviour of the World. Some believe the Holy Ghost took three drops of her Heart-blood, and disposed them in their place, to make the Body of our Lord. <hi>Salmeron,</hi> though<note place="margin">Tome 3. tract. 9.</note> he reject this Opinion, yet allows it to be a devout reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Contemplation. But he himself is of another mind, which I cannot give you in his terms, no more than I can the Opinions of other Authors upon this Occasion, because they search into the Mysteries of Generation so profoundly and exactly, and examin them in such a gross and naked manner, that even the chastest and most deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Translation of their <hi>Latin</hi> into <hi>English,</hi> would not fail to wound (or at least disorder) our Imagination. It would be worse yet, if I should recite any thing out of a Book, that was current in the last Age, (and it may be, is in being now) intituled <hi>Proto Evangelium, sive de Natalibus Christi, &amp; ipsius Matris V. Mariae,</hi> and Fathered on St. <hi>James.</hi> Here we may find enough to make the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65623:31"/> most shameless Prostitutes to blush; upon occasion of one <hi>Salome</hi> a Midwife, who would not believe a Virgin had brought forth, but would needs be as curious in her way, as St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> doubting of the Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was afterwards, in his. One <hi>William Postell,</hi> in the preceeding Age, made the discovery of this Horrible Gospel, God knows whence. But is it not a pretty ready way, to bring the True and Sacred Gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ into contempt?</p>
            <p>I will pass over all the impertinent tales with which they charge the Life of the Blessed Virgin. The care she took to keep the Fore-skin of our Lord, at his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision. The pains she was at to gather all the Blood and Water that fell from his hands, and feet, and side, upon the Cross; and in particular, the care she had to keep the Nails that fastened him thereto. I will pass over all this (I say) and a hundred such like things, to come to the last and greatest action of all, her <hi>Assump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> into Heaven, because it is one of the principal Stories on which the Worship of the Blessed Virgin is establish'd. Thus then the Gentlemen report the matter.</p>
            <p>The Blessed Virgin lived upon the Earth after her<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pelbart,</hi> who lived in the Year 1471. and dedicated his Book to Pope <hi>Sixt.</hi> IV.</note> Son, till she was Fifty Eight years old, as some say; Sixty Three, as others; and others, more by a great deal. At last she Prayed very earnestly to her Son, that she might depart from this place of Pilgrimage on Earth, and be gathered unto him; who thereupon sent an Angel to her, promising that within three days he would take her to himself. Together with this News, the Angel delivered her a branch of Palm that he brought from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise, and told her, she must have it carried before her Bier to her Interment; he gave her also a Suit of Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which her Son had sent her. Of this Angel she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded two things; first, that she might be buried by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65623:32"/> all the Apostles. Secondly, that when her Soul depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from her Body, it might meet with none of the Devils, or Malign Spirits. Upon which last demand, the Angel said unto her, <hi>Madam, why are you afraid to meet the Devil, whose Head it is that you have bruised? However what you ask, you shall have: You shall meet with no Devils, and the Noble Apostles shall Inter you.</hi> Upon this the Angel re-ascended into Heaven, environ'd with a great Light. And suddenly the branch of Palm that he had brought, and left in the Virgins hand, became exceeding bright, of a lively shining Green, and every leaf thereof as glorious as the Morning Star.</p>
            <p>To free you from all manner of doubt in this matter, St. <hi>Cosmus Vestitor</hi> (from whom honest <hi>Pelbert</hi> says he took this History,) tells us, he saw himself a little piece of this Branch, which retained to his days, a lustre, equal to a very bright Star.</p>
            <p>The Virgin, full of Joy at this good news, assembled all the Virgins and Saints together, and gave them to understand her Death was now at hand, comforting them thereupon. At the same time was St. <hi>John</hi> the Apostle Preaching at <hi>Ephesus,</hi> and in the middle of his Sermon, comes me a clap of Thunder, and a white Cloud, that whisk'd him through the Air, and set him down at the Door of the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> House; where being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, he and the Virgin embrac'd each other, with abundance of Tears, and <hi>Mary</hi> recommended to his care, her Burial. At which words, the good Apostle threw himself down upon the Earth, and with a great deal of passion cry'd out and said, <hi>Alas! My God, My God, Why dost thou lay this sore affliction upon us, to take away this Holy Mistress of our Religion, the Mirror of Sanctity, and our only Consolation?</hi> As he was thus lamenting, the Blessed Virgin shew'd him the shining Palm, and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65623:32"/> Mourning Suit her Son had sent her, and order'd him to take great care this Branch were carried before her Bier. St. <hi>John</hi> desir'd with all his heart, that all the Apostles might accompany him at this Solemn Action, and immediately the Apostles, that were scattered in all the corners of the Earth, were carried through the Air on white Clouds, and set down before the House, where entring in, and meeting with St. <hi>John,</hi> they were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellously astonished, but after Salutations, he explained the whole Mystery to them, upon hearing of which, they were overwhelmed with grief, and entering into <hi>Maries</hi> room, adored her, in the Angels Salutation, saying <hi>Ave Maria, gratia plena, &amp;c.</hi> to whom the Virgin replied saying, <hi>God preserve you, the chosen Disciples of my only Son.</hi> After a great deal of homage &amp; adoration paid unto her by the Apostles, she received the Communion, recommended her Spirit to her Son, kneeled down upon the ground, lift up her Soul to God, and disposed herself to give up the ghost. About the third hour of the Night, Jesus himself, with the nine Orders of Angels, the Assembly of Patriarchs, Prophets, Martyrs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors and Virgins, came down from Heaven, and stood about her Bed, the whole Coelestial Army singing Songs and admirable Hymns to the honour of <hi>Mary,</hi> Jesus himself beginning, and saying, <hi>Come my chosen, come, and I will place Thee on my Throne.</hi> To whom the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin answered, <hi>Lo, I come, as it is written in the Volume of the Book, that I should do thy will, O my God;</hi> and the reupon render'd up her Soul into the hands of her Son, who bore it away with him to Heaven. When the Soul was gone, the Body made shift of itself to say, <hi>I I give thee thanks, O Lord, for that I am thy glory; remem- Me, because I am the work of thy hands, and have kept what you committed to my charge;</hi> upon which the Body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65623:33"/> so luminous, that the Maids who were preparing it for Burial, and could touch it very well before, could not so much as look upon it. Now when all things were ready, and the body to be taken up, the Apostles made abundance of Complements and Ceremonies, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Places of Honour to one another round, with great civility; but at last it was agreed, that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> should carry the Corps, <hi>John</hi> should go before with the Palm, and the rest of the Apostles should fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in couples. As they were going forward, Jesus Christ march'd over them, with all his Angels, covered in a Cloud, and joyning Voices with the College of Apostles, they made an admirable Consort; and at the same time, a most sweet and fragrant Odour was spread through all the Region of the Air, on all hands.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> at this sight, being fill'd with rage and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, thought this a very fair opportunity to rid their hands at once, of all the Apostles of Jesus Christ, there met together; and gathering together, the High Priest himself advances first, and most profanely lays his two hands upon the Bier, to stop them; when lo! imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately they both withered, and were torn of at the elbows, and there hung on each side of the Corps, whilst the rest that followed him, were struck with blindness. The miserable High Priest made a lamentable howling for the loss of his hands, and for extreme anguish that he felt. But <hi>Peter</hi> told him honestly, there was no way to save himself, but by kissing the Bier where the Body of <hi>Mary</hi> lay, and making Profession of the Christian Faith, which he quickly did, and both his hands were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately fastened on again. A little after, <hi>Peter</hi> gave him one of the Dates that grew on the Branch of Palm, to rubb his Followers eyes with, who thereupon reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their sight. And now, without any further mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestation,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65623:33"/> they were come to the Vale of <hi>Jehosophat,</hi> where they found a Sepulchre hewn out of a Rock, and altogether like that of Jesus Christ; there they laid the Body of the Virgin, and continued three days in their Devotions at her Tomb. At the end of which, a bright Cloud shone all about the Sepulchre, the Voices of Angels ecchoed out from every quarter, a sweet smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Savour was spread throughout the Air, and all the World was seiz'd with ravishing astonishment. <hi>Jesus</hi> descended with his Angels, and having saluted his Apostles, said unto them, <hi>What Glory, and what Honour, think you, ought I to bestow upon my Mother?</hi> To which, with one consent, they answered, <hi>It seemeth just unto thy Servants, O Lord, that as Thou hast vanquished Death, and reignest from Generation to Generation, so also Thou shouldst raise the Body of thy Mother, and set her at thy right hand for evermore.</hi> The Soul of <hi>Mary</hi> presently appeared, and our Lord said to it, <hi>Arise my well beloved, the Tabernacle of Glory, thou art fair, my dear beloved, and there is no blemish in thee; as thou hast no spot, so shall thy Body never see corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus were things carried, according to the report of <hi>Pelbart</hi> of <hi>Temeswar,</hi> a grave Author, whom Father <hi>Crasset,</hi> a Jesuit, hath very lately cited abundance of<note place="margin">1 Part. tr. 1. quaest. 13. pag. 103.</note> times, (in his Book of <hi>True Devotion to the Virgin,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in 1679.) as worthy throughly to be believed; and <hi>Pelbart</hi> himself tells us, he had them from the Writings of St. <hi>Cosmus Vestitor</hi> Othersreport these matters a little otherwise, in the business of the Virgins Tomb, which (they say) stood open three days, by reason St. <hi>Thomas</hi> was absent, who earnestly desir'd (it would not be very fair to ask of whom he desir'd this, or how he came to know she was dead, but desire he did,) the Consolation of seeing the Body of <hi>Mary,</hi> which yet was not granted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65623:34"/> him, for he came, and found the Sepulchre was empty, and in the midst of it, a Spring of <hi>Manna</hi> boyling up.</p>
            <p>O God! what face is this, to forge so silly a Romance, for which there is not in good History, the least foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? For in a word, in all this Rapsody, there's not a sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Truth: And yet this is the bottom of the Worship and Adoration paid to the Blessed Virgin, and of the Feast of her <hi>Assumption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not my business to confute this Story of the <hi>Assumption,</hi> here; let it suffice, at present, that I adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise you, it was unknown to all the Ancients for the first four Centuries. That passage in the Chronicle of <hi>Eusebius,</hi> is acknowledg'd by Men of Understanding, to be false and spurious; as likewise are the Pieces attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to St. <hi>Austin</hi> and St. <hi>Jerom;</hi> together with the false <hi>Dionysius,</hi> who wrote between Four and Five Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, at the soonest. In a word, the Men of sense and honesty, even among the <hi>Romanists,</hi> do at this day look upon the <hi>Assumption,</hi> as an idle business, but I must not tell the People so. The Church of <hi>Paris</hi> seems to have declar'd openly against it; for by an Ordinance of the Cathedral Chapter of <hi>Nostre Dame,</hi> the First of <hi>August</hi> 1668, it was decreed, that such a certain long Sermon, or Homily, that had been read in the Quire the first Canonical hour, for many years last past, on the Fifteenth of <hi>August,</hi> the Feast of the <hi>Assumption,</hi> every year, should be read no more. (This Sermon, you must know, established the Assumption both of Body and Soul, and was added by I can't tell who, from the Year 1549. or 1550.) and that henceforwards should be read, what was usually read out of the Martyrology, taken from <hi>Ʋswardus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65623:34"/>
            <p>Now the passage in <hi>Ʋswardus,</hi> which the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">Who lived in the 9th. Cent.</note> and Bishop of <hi>Paris,</hi> ordered to be restored to its place, has these words: <hi>The Sleep or Death of</hi> Mary, <hi>the holy Mother of God.</hi>
               <q>Although her Sacred Body is not found on Earth, yet the Church, who is a pious Mother, celebrates her blessed Memory, not doubting in the least, but that She died according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all Mankind. But the Church being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate in her Judgments, hath rather chosen to own she knows not where this Sacred Temple of the Holy Ghost is hidden by the Providence of God, than teach any thing herein either Vain or Apocryphal.</q> These were the words, that were taken from the Service of the Feast of the Assumption, to thrust in a certain Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that taught just contrary; saying, the Church look'd upon the Assumption of the Blessed Virgins body and soul into Heaven, as a thing very sure and certain. <hi>Claudius Joly,</hi> Canon of the Church, and one of the<note place="margin">C. Joly de verbis Usuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di dissertatio. J. Launoii de controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia super ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribendo Martyrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio.</note> Commissaries, deputed to Examine this Affair, hath made a Dissertation thereupon. And the Learned <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur de Launoy,</hi> has given his Judgment on the same Subject, in whose works one may find enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found this Story of the <hi>Assumption,</hi> and answer <hi>Baronius</hi> and the rest, who look upon it as a point of Faith, or at least a Sacred History, that no body must touch, or offer once to disbelieve.</p>
            <p>What we have hitherto seen of the History of the Blessed Virgin, and on which the Worship that is paid to Her is founded, is but a little part of the Chronicle of the Mother of God. She has done more Miracles since her Death, than Jesus Christ and all his Apostles did in all their Lives, in all the World; and we have huge great Volumes of them, some of which I cannot forbear giving you for a taste, because the Worship of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65623:35"/> the Blessed Virgin is exceedingly Built, and Established on them, and because they are at this day thought the efficacious and powerful Arguments to defend their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition. And <hi>F. Crasset,</hi> Jesuit of repute, thought so to be sure, when in Answer to the Author of <hi>Sober advice to the Indiscreet Devotos of the Virgin</hi>—He makes this Use of them.</p>
            <p>In the number of these Fables, I put the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Places of Devotion, where the Virgin is parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly Worshipped, where She works great Miracles, and whither Her Devotos go on Pilgrimage; the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation I say of these Places, and their Holiness, is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on such Fables, as I verily believe Pagans would blush to own. Such, for Example, is that on which is founded the famous Worship of our Lady of <hi>Mount Serrat.</hi> We are told, the first Count of <hi>Barcelona</hi> had an exceeding handsome Daughter, but possessed with a Devil, whom the Count one day carried to a holy Man in the Neighbourhood, call'd Frier <hi>John Guerin,</hi> to the end he should exorcise the Devil, and deliver his Daughter: He did so, and for fear the Devil should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again into her, he advised the Count to leave her there some little time in his keeping; to which the Count consented, and accordingly left her. Frier <hi>John</hi> being alone with this handsome young Lady, (and not being able to quell his own Devil) became enamoured of her; and in short, Ravilh'd her first, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Kill'd her, at the instigation of a Devil disguised like a Hermite. After this, being guilty of these de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable Crimes, away he goes to <hi>Rome,</hi> there confesses himself to the Pope, who ordered him for Penance, to return to <hi>Mount Serrat</hi> upon all four, like a Beast as he was; and not to speak a word, nor offer to get up up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Legs, till a Child about three Months old should
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65623:35"/> bid him rise, and tell him God had pardoned his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Seven years after this, the Count of <hi>Barcelona</hi> was a Hunting, when some of his Men found out this Friet in a Den, all over hairy like a Bear, whom they took and Chained, and brought away with them to the Castle of <hi>Barcelona,</hi> where he was tied up in a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble like a Monster. The Count a little after made a great Feast, and to divert his Company, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Monster to be brought forth; whom as soon as the Earl's Child saw, that was there in its Nurses Arms, it said distinctly these words: <hi>Rise up upon thy Feet, Frier</hi> John Guerin, <hi>for God hath pardoned thy Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> And immediately the Frier came to himself, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to speak, and tell the whole Story. Upon which the Count told him, that since God had pardoned him, he could do no less. But however, he desired to know where he had buried his Daughter, that he might take up her Bones, and bury them in his Fathers Sepulchre. The good Frier conducted the Count's Servants to the place where he had Interr'd the Lady, and opening the Ground, they found her (Would you think it?) alive and well, as fresh, and as handsome as ever, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a little kind of streak like a Scarlet Thread, about her Neck, in the place where he had cut. The Maid spoke, and told them she owed her Life to the Blessed Virgin, to whom she had been Consecrated, and who preserved her (and indeed it was so) Miraculously. There they built a Convent, of which this young Lady was the <hi>Abbess,</hi> and Frier <hi>J. Guerin,</hi> the Confessor, Near to this place, in a certain Grotto, was found an<note place="margin">Ferreolus Locrius lib. 4. c. 25. Mariae Augustae.</note> Image of the Blessed Virgin, exceeding bright and lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous, and perfumed with excellent Sweets, which was discovered by Angels Melody, that were worship ping it in the Cave; this Image, they that found it,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65623:36"/> were for carrying away, but when they came as far as the place where the Lady had been buried, it grew so hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy on their Hands, that they were glad to leave it there with all their Hearts. There they built a Chappel over it, although it was a very desert place, and mighty incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the Pilgrims resorting thither; and this is the rise of that famous Chappel, where so many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and famous Things have been done.</p>
            <p>The Devotion of our Lady of <hi>Liesse,</hi> is founded on a Tale, no less ridiculous than the former, though it be something less horrible. We are told, that a certain Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, Daughter to the <hi>Soldan</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the time of the Holy Wars, (the Original of all Romances) came to visit three Gentlemen of <hi>Picardy,</hi> that were Prisoners at <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> and demanded of them the Picture of the Blessed Virgin. Not a Man of them understood a bit of Painting, but however one of them promised her Highness what she required; but being put very hard to fulfil it, the Virgin delivered them from their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, by giving them her Picture from Heaven her self. The Princess upon this, found means to break their Prison, and escape with them, and passing an arm of the Sea, they laid them down to sleep in a Wood, and waking in the Morning, found themselves in <hi>Picardy</hi> by a Fountain, where they built the Church of our Lady of <hi>Liesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of this kind, there is nothing in the World more Renowned, and at the same time more Absurd, than the History of the famous Chamber of our Lady of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retto.</hi> This is the very Chamber of the House of <hi>Joa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim</hi> and <hi>Ann,</hi> in the City of <hi>Nazareth</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> in which the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was Born. (Our Legendaries should consult with one another, sometimes, for before we heard She was Born in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> with a great deal
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65623:36"/> of Punctuality.) In this Chamber She received the Salutation of the Angel, in this Conceived the Saviour of the World, and in this bred Him up till He was Twelve Years of Age. The Apostles, after the Death of Jesus Christ, observing carefully what a world of Miracles were wrought in this Chamber, judged it very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to build a Chappel there, and Celebrate the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries in it, that is to say, to sing Mass in it; and Saint <hi>Luke</hi> the Evangelist, who was as good a Painter as Physician, drew with his own hand the Picture of the Virgin, which is there to be seen to this day. This Chappel was frequented with a great deal of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilst the Christians staid in <hi>Galilee,</hi> and especially in the time of the <hi>Croisades,</hi> or holy Wars, but the Christians being chased away, and the Devotion at this Chamber beginning to cool apace, the Angels took it on the <hi>9th.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> in the year, 1291. (says <hi>Turselin,</hi> very exactly) and brought it throught the Air into <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> distant from <hi>Galilee</hi> about Six thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Miles; as those who have cast it up tell us, upon whom let it rest. There the Angels set the Chamber or Chappel down upon a Hill, in view of the <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Sea, between two Towns, the one called <hi>Tersactum,</hi> and the other <hi>Flumen.</hi> At the first, there was a mighty concourse of devout People, that came upon the fame of this great Miracle, but their Zeal continued not; and the Virgin not finding there, the honour she expected, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Angels a second time to take the Room, and passing the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea, to Transport it into <hi>Italy,</hi> and set it down in the Territory of <hi>Recanati,</hi> in the midst of a Wood, belonging to a certain Lady (for without a Woman in the case, there can be no great Miracle) called <hi>Loretta,</hi> that owed the Diocess, or Territory of <hi>Recanati;</hi> which accordingly they did.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65623:37"/> This new Miracle of the second Transportation of the Chamber, rekindled Mens devotion for the Virgin, and there was old flocking to it from all Quarters, but the Situation of the Chappel was an occasion of a great many Robberies and Villanies committed on the poor Pilgrims, by reason that the Woods afforded shelter to the Rogues, who upon all occasions Sallied out upon them, and retir'd into the same securely. The Angels therefore thought it fit, it should be taken from amidst this Wood, and removed a little farther, to a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that belonged to two Brothers; which Brothers in a short time, made a very profitable business of it, by the great resort of Pilgrims, and the rich Presents that were made, but not being able to agree in the division of the Spoil, the Virgin was very angry, and thought they were unworthy of the honour She had done them, and therefore ordered the Angels to transfer it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place; up then they took it the fourth time, and set it in the High-way, where now it stands and works such Miracles. The People of <hi>Recanati</hi> came to see this Miraculous Room; and finding it set upon the Ground without any manner of Foundation, were greatly afraid it would fall down, and therefore built about it a huge and mighty thick Wall, which stands at this present to be seen. But no body could tell from whence this House came, till a long time after, when the Blessed Virgin appeared in a Dream to a certain Man, an intimate Friend and Servant of Hers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed the whole matter to him, as I have been rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it. This Man declared the same to a certain Wise and Understanding Person of that Country, who thought it convenient, to depute sixteen Grave and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable Men, to go to <hi>Nazareth</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> and take Cognizance of the matter of Fact. Away they went,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65623:37"/> taking the Measure of the House at <hi>Loretto</hi> with them, and came safe to <hi>Nazareth,</hi> where they found an empty space, where the Virgins House had stood, and nothing left but the Foundations, of which these Sixteen took the Length and Breadth, and finding them to agree most exactly with the Dimensions of <hi>Loretto-House,</hi> they were sufficiently convinced; but besides, they found an Inscription on the Wall hard by, attesting that such a Church had stood there heretofore, and was Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculously carried away. And thus this truth was laid open as manifest as the Light, by the Testimony of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most a Jury and half of able Ambassadors, and this we find written in the Registers of that House, and hung up in a Table in the Chappel, to be seen by all Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. This is in effect, an <hi>Epitome</hi> of <hi>Tursellin</hi>'s great<note place="margin">Tursellin's Historiae Laure tanae, lib. 1.</note> History of this House, who amplifies the Matter very curiously. This Jesuit's Book was Printed with Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the VIII, with the general Approbation of the greatest Doctors at <hi>Rome,</hi> such as <hi>Raynaud, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ovius, Spondanus,</hi> and others, who refer us to this Book as a Piece, that is able to ease us of all manner of Doubts, that may rise on this occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And will the time then never come, when Men will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>assume that Shame they have so long renounc'd? How is it possible they can in Earnest, propagate such Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences as this? <hi>Cui bono,</hi> To what end and purpose is it, that a House must jump from place to place thus through the Air? Who does not see that this is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ne who is not the Father of Truth, to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold those lamentable Superstitions, of which that Blessed Maid is made the Object?</p>
            <p>It may be convenient here to observe, that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Transportation is said to have been made, at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65623:38"/> end of the Thirteenth Century, when the <hi>Saracens</hi> had entirely chased the <hi>Christians</hi> out of <hi>Palestin:</hi> And yet St. <hi>Antonine,</hi> A. B. of <hi>Florence,</hi> one of the hardiest Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, and greatest Admirers of Fabulous Miracles, and strange things, that perhaps the World ever had, says not one word of this Matter; and yet he should have known, being an <hi>Italian,</hi> and living within 150. years of the time assigned for this great Wonder, and one that would have believed it, if he had but once heard on't. Another Saint also of the same Order, (a <hi>Dominican</hi>) and same Country, to wit, <hi>Vincent Ferrier,</hi> that lived according to <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Account, 1410. or as others say, in 1440. in a Sermon (amongst his Works) on the Feast of the <hi>Assumption,</hi> says expressly, that our Ladies Chamber is still at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and yet according to the History, it had been then in <hi>Italy,</hi> above 100. years; And was it not possible that great Saint should not know as much? But thus it is, The Fable was at first invented without any Conscience, without any Shame, or indeed, without any Discretion; God so permitting it, for the father evidencing this great Truth, that we might more easily see on what grounds all this kind of Worship is founded. But now for a Sample or two of Miracles.</p>
            <p>We are not to doubt, but as She is the most Glorious, She is also the most Holy, and by consequence, the humblest of all Women. But <hi>Papism</hi> has made Her a very pattern of Pride and Ambition, always aiming at Divine Honours; angry with all that pay them not, severely Punishing those that offend Her, and Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensing amply all that are peculiarly devoted to Her, and working Miracles perpetually, for nothing but to acquire Adoration, and Honour to Her self. To esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish this Adoration, they have made such a Romance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65623:38"/> of the Blessed Virgin, that no good sober Heathen would have done the like to his <hi>Minerva</hi> or <hi>Diana,</hi> Goddesses of Chastity.</p>
            <p>For Example. What more could any Servant of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> or of <hi>Flora,</hi> Goddesses of Prostitution, say of their Deities, than has been said of <hi>Mary,</hi> when they make her marry St. <hi>Dominick.</hi> This Saint was in a Cavern, where he was doing Penances, alas! for the <hi>Albigenses</hi> of <hi>Tholouse,</hi> covered with gore and wounds of his own inflicting. To him the Virgin appeared, accompanied with three Women, each of them being attended with fifty other Women; these were (Oh horror to relate!) this three Person of the Holy Trinity, that made up<note place="margin">Alanus redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivus p. 2. c. 3.</note> the Nuptial Equipage and Pomp, when the Virgin was to marry <hi>Dominick;</hi> and coming to him, <hi>Dominick</hi> (said she) <hi>my Son, my dear Husband, because thou hast valiantly fought against the Enemies of the Faith, lo I am come to succour thee, I, (I say) whom thou so oft has call'd upon.</hi> Then the three Queens that accompanied her, lift up St. <hi>Dominick</hi> from the ground, where he lay half dead, and the Virgin received him into her embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, kissing him lovingly and tenderly, and withal opened her breasts and let him suck, till he was perfectly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. In what a hot and furious imagination was the impudent Monk, think you, when he wrote these hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things? Came he not reeking from his damn'd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches, to commit these foul impurities to paper? I appeal to all Persons in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, of pious Minds and chast Thoughts, nay, to all the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the Blessed Virgin, that have any sense of Vertue, any touch of shame, to all such I appeal for my just indignation against this. <hi>Alanus de Rupibus,</hi> (for he it is that reports these things, and that writes of the like abominable intercourse betwixt the Virgin
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65623:39"/> and himself says, he was usually tempted of the Devil, once in every seven years, and in one of these fits, he had like to have cut his own Throat for<note place="margin">Idem ibid. part 2. c. 4.</note> despair; but at Mid-night the Virgin came into his Cell, and after a great deal of discourse, drew out her Breasts, and milk'd them on the wounds the Devil had made, and cured them perfectly. Afterwards she married her Servant in the presence of Jesus Christ, and a great many Saints there present, giving him her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Ring, made of her Virgin-hair. After this, she put about his neck a Chain or String, made likewise of her hair, with a hundred and fifty Precious-stones, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of Beads in the Virgins <hi>Psalter</hi> or <hi>Chaplet.</hi> After, she gave him a sweet Kiss, and let him suck her Virgin-Breasts, which he doing very greedily, seemed to have all his Body bedewed with a sweet Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor; and this favour, he says, she afforded him fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently. Another Story tells us, that one <hi>Eustochium</hi> a Religious Nun, having begg'd of the Virgin to see the Child Jesus, she found him laid upon the straw, where she fell to kissing and embracing him so ardently, that she thought she should have died for pleasure, on the place. Another young Maid, about Fourteen, a devout Servant of the Virgins, having ask'd the same thing, <hi>Mary</hi> gave him into her arms, who embrac'd, caress'd and kiss'd him with such violent transports of love, that her very heart was cleft asunder. Fair warning, one would think, to young Maids!</p>
            <p>Has either <hi>Alcoran,</hi> or <hi>Jewish Talmud,</hi> Stories so lewd and so abominable as these? Yet these are the Authors, whose Authority <hi>F. Crasset</hi> has within these six last years, renewed and re-established in his Book! But what is the design of these tales? Why, 'tis to establish the Worship of the Blessed Virgin; for St. <hi>Dominick</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65623:39"/> been her Husband, but that he invented the <hi>Rosary,</hi> otherwise call'd the <hi>Virgins Psalter,</hi> compos'd of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Beads, of which there are fifteen <hi>Pater Nosters</hi> for God, (and well they can spare them too,) and and one hundred thirty five <hi>Ave Maria's</hi> for the Virgin. And for the same reason was our Friend <hi>Alan</hi> favoured, because the Rosary-way of Worship beginning to decay, he did what in him lay to revive it. And for the two Virgins obtaining the favour to Kiss Jesus Christ in the Flesh, even to Swooning away, why was it, but because they were devoted to the Service of the Virgin in a more peculiar manner? Now, that you may not think these fearful Examples are but few in number, you must know there are abundance of them in all the Authors that <hi>F. Cras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set</hi> quotes and admires. <hi>Hautin,</hi> a Jesuit like himself, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a History from <hi>Surius,</hi> of the Marriage of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> with one <hi>Herman,</hi> surnamed <hi>Joseph,</hi> (because they were both of them married to the Virgin,) to whom the Virgin came, accompanied with two Angels, one of which began to speak and say, <hi>To whom shall we marry this Young Man?</hi> To <hi>Mary,</hi> replied the other, at which they commanded <hi>Herman</hi> to draw near: Poor <hi>Herman</hi> knew not what in the earth to do; Love prick'd him on, and Shame-fac'dness pull'd him back; for though<note place="margin">Hautin An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus Custos c. 4. numb. 3.</note> before-times he had had particular intimacy with the Blessed Virgin, yet he could never hope to see himself advanc'd to such a degree, as to be married to Her. <hi>Caesarius</hi> also, whom <hi>F. Crasset</hi> quotes as a very sincere<note place="margin">Caesarius l. 7. c. 13, 18, 32, 52.</note> Author, relates the Story of a Soldier that fell in love with his Captain's Wife, and following the advice of a good Hermit, saluted the Virgin a hundred times a day, who to recompence this civility, offered herself to him like an exceeding handsom Woman, saying, <hi>I will be thy Wife, come kiss me,</hi> and forc'd him to it. In the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65623:40"/> same Author, we find the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> kissing and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing Monks very liberally: Some she watches over whilst they sleep: others she wipes the face of, whilst they sleep, with her Handkerchief. And had I not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to say the Chronicles of <hi>Diana</hi> and <hi>Minerva</hi> were more chastly deliver'd down, than those of the ever Blessed Mother of our Lord?</p>
            <p>After these savours, it would be vain to produce any more, or others; but you may be assured there is no sort or kind, with which the <hi>Devoto's</hi> to the Virgin have not some time or other been graced. She has kept them in their Sicknesses; She has given them their Sight; She has delivered them from extreme dangers both by Sea and Land, from Thieves, from Fire, from the Gibbet, from Prisons, and from Death itself; for many have been raised from the dead, only because they or their Parents have been religious Worshippers of the Blessed Virgin. Read but <hi>Chronicon S. Ʋ. Deiparae,</hi> where you shall find a thousand Instances. If one should collect together all the deliverances God hath wrought from the beginning of the World, to this day, they would not make a History to compare with those wrought by our Lady of <hi>Loretto, Mont Serrat, Liesse, Hall, Moyenpont, Aspremont, Ardiliers,</hi> and a hundred more, and all to persuade Us, that the Virgin is mightily pleased to see Herself adored, and that she is at a stand sometimes to find out what Favours to bestow on her peculiar Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>But that which is most abominable, is, that these Fables would persuade Us, that the Service of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin is of greater benefit to Us, than that of God; and that, provided a Man dedicate himself to Her Service, let him be otherwise never so wicked a Villain, yet he need not despair of his Salvation. It was one of these
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65623:40"/> profane Visions St. <hi>Brigit</hi> pretended to have had, and which <hi>F. Crasset</hi> hath mustered up afresh, to the intent you should not think those Opinions were at all altered<note place="margin">Part 1. tr. 1. qu. 10. p. 77.</note> since those days, 1370. <hi>Sinners</hi> (says he) <hi>being her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, make up her Crown and Glory, and 'tis for that she loves them, with the tenderness and sweet compassion of a Mother, let them be never so wicked, as a Mother pittieth her Children, though they have lost their sences, and are become mad;</hi> and this is what she has revealed to St. <hi>Brigit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brig. Revel. book 6. c. 10.</note>
               <hi>Know Thou</hi> (quoth the Mother to the Daughter) <hi>my dearest Child, that there is no Man in the World so lewd and curs'd of God, that is entirely for saken of him whilst he lives; no Sinner so desperate, but may return, and find mercy with him, provided he have recourse to Me.</hi> St. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> is of the same mind, and expresses himself in these comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table words: <hi>O</hi> Mary, <hi>be a Man never so miserable a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, you have the soft compassions of a Mother for him; you embrace him, and hug him close in your bosom, and never will forsake him, till you have reconcil'd him to his formidable Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis with design of persuading us to believe these comfortable Truths, that F. <hi>Crasset</hi> musters up a whole Chapter of Examples of the wickedest Men that possibly can be, that yet have been saved, by preserving their<note place="margin">Ubi supra. pag. 36.</note> devotion for the Blessed Virgin, amidst all their impieties, entire. Such a one is that of <hi>Theophilus</hi> of <hi>Adanus,</hi> a City of <hi>Cilicia,</hi> who having been depos'd of his Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaconry, for no great good, gave himself over to the Devil, for spite and anger, by the help and means of a <hi>Jewish</hi> Magician whom he served. He renounced <hi>Mary</hi> and her Son, and gave the Devil a Scroll signed with his own Hand; after which he became intolerably despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and mad for what he had done: But in these Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Mind and Soul, a glimpse or ray of hope appeared
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65623:41"/> to him, that Blessed <hi>Mary</hi> could deliver him from this evil, and straightways thereupon he goes to her Church, and prostrates himself before her Image: Which failed him not at this time of need, but reconciled him to God, and forced the Devil to give him back his Bonds again.</p>
            <p>To this, F. <hi>Crasset</hi> thinks fit to add such another,<note place="margin">Pag. 90. part 1.</note> taken from <hi>Caesarius;</hi> of a young <hi>Gascoign</hi> Soldier, who after he had wasted all he had in the World, gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self up to <hi>Satan,</hi> and renounced <hi>Jesus Christ;</hi> but do whatever the Devil could, he could not be brought to renounce his Mother, and this obtained his Pardon for that horrible Crime; down he threw himself before the Image of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which had the Image of <hi>Jesus</hi> in her arms, and heard this Dialogue between them. The Virgins Image said, <hi>O my sweet Son, have mercy on this Man:</hi> The Son's Image answered, <hi>Why Mother, what would you have me do with this Wretch, that hath renounced Me?</hi> After this, the young Man saw the Blessed Virgin (that is to say, her Image) prostrate herself to little <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> and demand again his Pardon, whom <hi>Jesus</hi> lovingly took up, (and 'twas very much for a Child of his big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,) and said to her, <hi>I never yet refused my Mother any thing she ask'd; I grant it for your sake, and yours alone.</hi> Would one believe, that a Jesuit should have the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to furbish up such ridiculous things as these, at this time of day, in such an Age as ours? I had often heard this Story told by Protestants, to shame the Papists; but I never thought it would have been produced at this time, by a Renowned Jesuit, in honour of their Religion, and that too in <hi>Paris,</hi> the most frequented City in the whole World. But to put you past all doubting of this Truth, F. <hi>Crasset</hi> tells us, that <hi>Caesarius</hi> says, that this very <hi>Gascoign</hi> was alive in his time, 1222. and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was more sure, nor better attested, than this famous
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65623:41"/> Story. And for the credit of <hi>Caesarius,</hi> the same good Father tells us, he was of the Order of <hi>Cistercians,</hi> and lived above four hundred years ago, and was, as <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themius</hi> the Abbot tells us, a very Learned, and a very<note place="margin">Pag. 105.</note> Honest Man, and one that stuck to his rule very close. You may judge (says he) of the sincerity and credit of this Man, by what he says in his Preface to his own Works, <hi>God is my Witness</hi> (cries he) <hi>that I am not the Inventer of any thing I have reported in my Dialogues.</hi> And who alive can help believing him, after this Protestation? Therefore take, in short, another Story of <hi>Caesarius</hi>'s tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, of one <hi>Beatrix</hi> a Servant in a Convent, who being debauch'd by a Priest, got out of the Convent, and lived in a Bawdy-house fifteen years, during all which time, the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> took her shape, and constantly supplied her place; so that no body perceiv'd her absence, and her Reputation suffered nothing all the while; and all this, because she had, as she was going out, prayed to the Virgin, and (giving her the Keys of the Convent into her hand) had said, <hi>Madam, I have served you as devoutly</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caesarius l. 7. c. 35.</note>
               <hi>as I possibly could; I give you here your Keys again, and am able no longer to withstand the temptations of the Flesh.</hi> This tends to the same end with all the rest, namely, to let you understand, that, break God's Commands, or do<note place="margin">Crass. p. 90.</note> whatever you please, serve but the Blessed Virgin, and all is well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pelbart</hi> of <hi>Temeswar,</hi> another of F. <hi>Crasset's</hi> great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,<note place="margin">Stell. Coronae. l. 12. c. 3.</note> tells us, there was a certain Woman that plaid the Whore with a Neighbor's Husband of hers, whose Wife finding his roguery out, pray'd to the Virgin to confound that wicked Creature that had debauch'd her Husband from her Bed; but it was found, that this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Harlot had still the grace, every day, to say seven <hi>Ave Maria's,</hi> and therefore the Virgins Image answered
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65623:42"/> the complaining Wife, and said, <hi>She of whom thou speakest, offers me Praises that are very agreeable to me, and whilst she does so, I assure you Mistress I can never hurt her, but on the contrary, will preserve her from disgrace; however I promise you, I'll see and convert her.</hi> And this is the way to Proselyte to the Virgin, those who trample God's Commandments under foot.</p>
            <p>If you would have any more Stories, to prove that the Worship of the Virgin separate from that of God, is a sure way to Salvation, you may find them, in great<note place="margin">Crasset. p. 94.</note> plenty, in Father <hi>Crasset.</hi> There you may see the Virgin keeping them, that keep not God's Commands; and how a Bird having learn'd to cry <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> and being seized on by a Hawk, scream'd out but <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> and the ravenous Hawk immediately left her. And likewise, how the Devil, being in the Air, and spying a Christian that was not upon his guard, came swooping down upon him, like a Bird of Prey; but as soon as he heard him pronounce, and devoutly call upon the Name of <hi>Mary,</hi> he was fain to pull in his horns (I meant his talons) and be gone. There you shall see her taking a great deal of pains to raise from the dead, Rogues that had liv'd in nothing else but wickedness, &amp; died without repentance; only to give them leisure to Confess, and do some trifling Penances, and then again depart in peace. It is the same Father <hi>Crasset,</hi> that tells from <hi>Surius,</hi> the History of a Citizen of <hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Andrew,</hi> so insufferably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd, that he bore no token or mark of Christianity upon him, but that he was an Admirer of St. <hi>Caesarion</hi> Martyr: As <hi>Andrew</hi> lived, so he died like a Reprobate, without any tokens of Repentance; but at the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Caesarion,</hi> he arose from the dead to Confess, and do Penance, and returned from whence he came.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:65623:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pelbart</hi> of <hi>Temeswar</hi> (that never sticks at any thing) tells us of a Robber on the High-way, (that used nevertheless to Fast every <hi>Saturday</hi> in Honour to the Virgin) who at last being caught in the Fact, was Beheaded on the spot; his Head in falling from his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, cried out thrice, <hi>Confession, Confession, Confession,</hi> upon which they fetch'd a Priest, who came and set his Head again upon his Shoulders, to whom the Thief reported, that as soon as his Head was cut off, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils had seised on his Soul to drag it into Hell, but that the Virgin hindred them, not permitting the Soul and Body quite to separate, till he was Confess'd; and that he had obtained this Grace, for Fasting every <hi>Saturday</hi> to her Honour: And this serves to support two Articles of Popery, the Invocation of the Virgin, and the necessity of Confession. But if we will not believe <hi>Pelbart,</hi> nor Father <hi>Crasset,</hi> neither will we Hereticks be persuaded, that a Rogue rose from the dead.</p>
            <p>In the same place, you read how that the Soul of a Soldier kill'd in Fight, in the Service of the Emperor <hi>Sigismond,</hi> continued in his Body many years after the Flesh was rotten and worn off. The Blessed Virgin not permitting the Soul to part before Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssion, because he had been all his Life time Her peculiar Servant. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Miracle there is, of which <hi>Pelbart</hi> himself was an Eye-witness. A certain wicked Villain fell into the <hi>Danube,</hi> and was under water three days, where he heard a Voice say to him, Thou deservest well, O Wretch, to lose thy Life, and be Condemn'd for ever for thy Sins, but because thou art a Servant to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> thou shalt be delivered from this danger, that thou may'st go and be Confessed; and up he came, though he could not Swim a stroke, and came and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess'd to <hi>Pelbart</hi> himself, who tells you this Story. <hi>'Twas
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65623:43"/> from the Man his own self</hi> (says Father Crasset) <hi>that this Religious</hi> Pelbart <hi>heard this History; and you must either believe this Penitent was an Impostor and Cheat,</hi> (and I pray take heed of wronging such a Pickled Youth) <hi>or else that</hi> Pelbart <hi>was a wicked Man, and took delight to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 135.</note>
               <hi>impose upon the belief of the soveraign High Priest of</hi> Rome, (<hi>to whom he dedicated his Works) and all the Faithful. Or else you must believe this Story for a certain truth, and consequently that the Virgin does preserve some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times her Servants from everlasting Damnation, after Death.</hi> And in the same Page, this worthy <hi>Jesuit</hi> says, That <hi>Caesarius</hi> the <hi>Cistercian,</hi> that lived about 400. years since, and made 12. Books of Dialogues upon Miracles and Apparitions in his time, sets down many Examples of this nature; how Dead men were saved from Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by the Virgins means, obtaining Grace for them, to return to Life again to do some Penance.</p>
            <p>If I would drain those Springs (as Father <hi>Crasset</hi> does) of <hi>Pelbart, Caesarius, Bernardin de Bustis, Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Bellovicensis,</hi> St. <hi>Antonine</hi> of <hi>Florence,</hi> and the rest, I could make a monstrous great Volume of these Fables, that tend to the establishing the necessity of Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Blessed Virgin, but this small number drawn from Father <hi>Crasset,</hi> is as good as if I had heaped up all together, with a great deal of Pains and Trouble.</p>
            <p>For by this, we Protestants may see, how far we are to trust those <hi>Catholick Doctors,</hi> who would have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, their Service and Religion has for many years last past, been cleansed and purified from all these vain and idle Popular Superstitions. When Father <hi>Crasset,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Jesuit, (though Monsieur <hi>Arnaud</hi> call him the <hi>Wretched Jesuit Crasset</hi>). A Jesuit, I say, in the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> where Popery is most refin'd; in the Face of <hi>Monsieur,</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> and other Catholicks,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65623:43"/> averse from the vulgar Superstitions. When he, I say again, renews and revives these Silly and Impertinent Fables, with the approbation of his Society, his Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Bishop, and his King. And if the great Man at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of Louis le Grand.</note> should in a good Humour, think fit to say, this Book of Father <hi>Crasset,</hi> is composed with <hi>so much Learning, in▪ such a Method, and with such a Discretion, as is proper to instruct the Readers clearly in few words, and to extort even from the unwilling (such as</hi> Monsieur de Meaux, <hi>and</hi> Monsieur Arnaud) <hi>a confession of the Catholick Faith.</hi> (In this point) If he, I say, should but say thus much, I would fain know why it would not be as Authentick a Book, as the <hi>Catholick Exposition</hi> of <hi>Monsieur de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And are we (in good earnest) secure, it never will be so? Will a better Friend to the Jesuits, never possess that Chair? And if there do, may he not do as much for such a Book as this of Father <hi>Crassets,</hi> as the present Pope has done for <hi>Monsieur de Meaux</hi>'s? And must the Faith of Christ be at such uncertainties? This surely is not building on a Rock, but on the Sand, that every Wave can wash away at pleasure. For if every Pope ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake an Exposition of the Catholick Faith, Authentical, (And if every one cannot, how can any one?) I do not see but we may have as many several Faiths, as there are Casualties and Diseases in the Weekly Bill.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:65623:44"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Tho. Newborough, <hi>at the</hi> Star <hi>in St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Travels of Monsieur de <hi>Thevenot</hi> into the <hi>Levant,</hi> in Three Parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Into I. <hi>Turkey.</hi> II. <hi>Persia.</hi> III. The <hi>East-Indies.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>R. Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ii, <hi>Commentaria de Rebellione Anglicana ab Anno 1640. usque ad Annum 1685. Pars Prima.</hi> Octa.</p>
            <p>A Paraphrase with Notes, and a Preface on the Sixth Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> shewing that there is neither good Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>son nor sufficient Authority, to suppose that the Eucharist is discoursed of in that Chapter, much less to infer the Doctrine of Transubstantiation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it, Quarto.</p>
            <p>Wholesome Advices from the Blessed Virgi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discreet Worshippers. Written by one of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion.</p>
            <p>Humanity and Charity of Christians. A Sermon Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the <hi>Suffolk</hi> Feast, <hi>November,</hi> 30. 1686. by <hi>W. Claget.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Present State of the Controversie between the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65623:44"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>